<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A beam of light, shining in the midst of much darkness and confusion: being (with the benefit of retrospection) an essay toward the stating (and fixing upon its true and proper basis) the best cause under heaven: viz. the cause of God, of Christ, of his people, of the whole creation, that groans and waits for the manifestation of the sons of God. By Chr. Feake, preacher of the gospel of the Kingdom of Jesus Christ.</title>
            <author>Feake, Christopher, fl. 1645-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85172</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866765</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119051</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240952669</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F567</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E980_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207729</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866765</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99866765e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85172)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119051)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 145:E980[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A beam of light, shining in the midst of much darkness and confusion: being (with the benefit of retrospection) an essay toward the stating (and fixing upon its true and proper basis) the best cause under heaven: viz. the cause of God, of Christ, of his people, of the whole creation, that groans and waits for the manifestation of the sons of God. By Chr. Feake, preacher of the gospel of the Kingdom of Jesus Christ.</title>
                  <author>Feake, Christopher, fl. 1645-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, by J.C. for Livewell Chapman, at the Crown in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 2".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Second Advent --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119051:1"/>
            <p>A BEAM OF LIGHT, SHINING In the midst of much <hi>Darkness</hi> and <hi>Confusion:</hi> Being (With the Benefit of Retrospection) An ESSAY toward the stating (and fixing upon its true and proper Basis) <hi>The Best Cause under Heaven: VIZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Cause of God, of Christ, of his People, of the whole Creation, that groans and waits for the manifestation of the Sons of God.</p>
            <p>By CHR. FEAKE, Preacher of the Gospel of the Kingdom of Jesus Christ.</p>
            <q>The Light shineth in Darkness, and the darkness comprehendeth it not, <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh. 1.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Unto the upright, there ariseth Light in the Darkness, <bibl>
                  <hi>Psal. 112.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>Livewell Chapman,</hi> at the Crown in <hi>Popes-head</hi> Alley. 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:119051:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119051:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE, TO All the Children of Light, who are not yet so wise in their Generation, as are the Children of this World. Grace, Mercy, and Peace, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>AS the Light of the Day dispels the Darkness of the Night; so the day of Truth and Wisdom, returning upon the world, beings to chase away before its face, the Night of falshood and folly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Dragon, <hi>the</hi> Beast, <hi>the</hi> false Prophet, <hi>the</hi> Mother of Harlots, <hi>the</hi> Kings of the Earth, who commit Fornication with her, <hi>have had a long time to act their part upon the face of the earth: but their time, and their Domination are both Bounded, and must ere long expire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The</hi> Lion of Judah's Tribe, the Lamb of God, <hi>(that takes away the sins of the world) the</hi> True Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, sent from God; <hi>the</hi> Bride, the Lambs wife; <hi>The</hi> Kings and the Priests which are to reign upon
<pb facs="tcp:119051:3"/>the Earth, <hi>will take their opportunity to supplant the supplanters, and put them all out of possession: behold, it will shortly come to pass.</hi> Amen. Halleluiah.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Lord is returning to</hi> visit and Redeem his people.
<note place="margin">Luk. 1.68, 69.</note> He is raising up an Horn of salvation for us, in the house of his servant <hi>David,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Now though these</hi> good words <hi>and</hi> these comfortable words <hi>were primarily intended for the Jewes, that waited for the Messiah; yet we Gentiles may plead for a portion also:
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.29.</note> for,</hi> is the Lord the God of the Jews only? is he not also of the Gentiles? yes, of the Gentiles also.
<note place="margin">15.12.</note>
               <hi>As it is written,</hi> There shall be a Root of <hi>Jesse,</hi> and He that shall rise to reign over the Gentiles, in him shall the Gentiles trust. <hi>And again, he saith,</hi> Rejoyce ye Gentiles with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We, who dwell afar off from</hi> Judea, <hi>in these Islands of the Sea, have seen, in our Daies, very strange and extraordinary Mutations and shakings, as if the old Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth were giving place</hi> to the new Heavens,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.13.</note> and to the new earth, wherein dwelleth righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. <hi>But suddenly, a sentence of Death seems to be passed upon all our hopes, by a violent Hurry back again towards our</hi> House of Bondage. <hi>In which He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricane, many professors, both Ministers and people,</hi> have made shipwrak of Faith and of a good Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>The true Disciples have obtained a check upon the winds and the seas, and there begins to be a great calm. In this happy interval, some of us desire, before the next storm ariseth, to be searching out those rich commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which in the late tempest were almost heav'd over-board, and to be securing them in a place of safety.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119051:3"/>
            <p>That which maketh manifest, is Light: <hi>And therefore, in our search after the</hi> Glorious Cause <hi>pleaded in these Nations, it was judged necessary to bring Matters of Fact into publick view, in order to a distinct understanding of</hi> that particular Interest <hi>which</hi> God <hi>himself hath owned and pleaded over and over, upon his</hi> British Stage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It's hoped, that what is written, may be somewhat usefull in such an hour as this is. Some, it may be, will take offence; but</hi> blessed is he that is not offended at the Prince of Princes, <hi>nor with his Cause.
<note place="margin">The Army cannot recal their words.</note> The Word is passed out of the Armies Mouth, it cannot be recalled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are a People, resolved to</hi> improve their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, <hi>which they themselves, for ought appears, have no heart to improve or promote for the present; the language of their late papers, being as a Barbarian to their Papers nine or ten years since.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some other passages, it may be, will be look'd upon, as not so sober and so serious, as they ought to have been: but to deal ingenuously, we must needs say, that the</hi> Ridiculousness <hi>of the spirit of</hi> High Presbytery,
<note place="margin">The Spirit of High Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery very ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous.</note>
               <hi>was such, at some certain times and seasons, as that we could not, but laugh it to scorn, even as before the Lord: for, was it a Time, when the</hi> promised Liberty of the Sons of God <hi>was coming forth in</hi> power and great glory, <hi>for our equals to design a</hi> Superintendency <hi>over us, more strict and rigid, then that of the late Episcopacy? No, no, we could lawfully laugh at that folly: they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to have been the</hi> Domineering Prelates <hi>Heirs and Successors, and so to have reigned in their stead, as</hi> Lords over Gods Heritage: <hi>but stay, Sirs,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 6.3.</note> that must not be:</hi> Lordly Prelacy <hi>was not thrown out of the saddle, that</hi> High Presbytery <hi>might be mounted like a
<pb facs="tcp:119051:4"/>Knight with his gilt spurs. The</hi> Honest Sectaries <hi>could not dream of becoming so tame a Beast, as to be ridden and spur'd by their fellow-sufferers: we could tell them, (with good reason too) No more Sectaries then themselves. But, as for those Brethren of the</hi> Classical-way, <hi>who are of a modest, sober spirit, and who live in</hi> true Self-denial and tenderness of Conscience, <hi>(being altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the workings of a</hi> pert, imposing Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position) <hi>We are one with them in the Centre and Root of</hi> Brotherly Love. <hi>And, if Misunderstandings could be removed, are ready to live and die with them for the Lords sake, and his Cause sake,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The reason of mentioning the Meeting of some</hi> Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries <hi>at</hi> Alhallows <hi>and</hi> Blackfryers, <hi>in the time of the Armies Declination; is, because there was, in those As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies, kept up and maintained a</hi> publick Testimony <hi>to that very Cause which they had declared for, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward turned their back upon: and we are perswaded, it was of great use to the</hi> faithful Remnant, <hi>who</hi> had escaped the corruptions which were in the world through lust, and did love the Lord Jesus Christ <hi>and his Cause, in sincerity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>One</hi> principal Reason <hi>of penning the</hi> ensuing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, <hi>was the</hi> great silence <hi>in that noble and notable cause contended for; little or no mention being made, in any of those many Papers which have passed through City and Countrey of late daies, concerning it; and therefore it was agreed among us, that something for the</hi> Name and Interest of the Approaching King of Saints, <hi>should be published to the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It's more then probable,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.13, 14.</note> that as Paul</hi> preached the Gospel to the <hi>Galatians</hi> through the infirmity of the flesh, <hi>so we shall be found to plead this Cause, with much of Humane frailty intermingled: but as they did
<pb facs="tcp:119051:4"/>not</hi> despise his temptation which was in his Flesh, <hi>because of the excellency of the message which he brought; so it is to he hoped, that for the Cause sake, which is in it self so very glorious, the children of the Free-woman, will over look and wink at, those</hi> Imperfections <hi>and</hi> Impertinencies <hi>which may be found in the Instrument that serves the providence of God in this matter. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, all is submitted to the deliberate Judgement of him that is spiritual, who being of</hi> perfect age, hath by reason of use, his senses exercised to discern both good and evil. <hi>And the Lord do with us, and with this Essay,</hi> as seemeth good in his own eyes.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London, <date>20. 3. m. 1659.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Signed in the Name, and on the behalf of a little Remnant of the Lords People,</hi> CHR. FEAKE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:119051:5"/>
            <p>THe Author and the Printer are very unwilling the Reader should be hindered by any faults or mistakes that usually and unavoydably do occur in all Books that pass the Press: Wherefore it is desired, the Amendments following may be observed and inserted, as is directed.</p>
            <p>Page 8. line 30. for <hi>proceeding,</hi> read <hi>proceedings.</hi> pag. 19. l. 1. &amp;c. read <hi>Model.</hi> p. 20. l. 16. for <hi>of Wales,</hi> read <hi>in Wales</hi> p. 31. l. 5. for <hi>mens,</hi> read <hi>men.</hi> p. 31. in the Margin, last line save one, for <hi>them,</hi> read <hi>that.</hi> The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Reader will observe the Points, and every defective Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thesis, as he meets with them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119051:5"/>
            <head>A BEAM of LIGHT Shining in the Midst of Much <hi>Darkness</hi> and Confusion: Being, (With the Benefit of Retrospection) An ESSAY toward the stating (and fixing upon its true and proper Basis) <hi>the Best Cause under Heaven.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I. <hi>A Preface or Introduction, toward the stating of the Cause; the low condition of the Puritans, a little before the Troubles in</hi> Scotland; <hi>the Insolency of the perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Party in Church and State; the Short Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> April <hi>the</hi> 13. 1640. <hi>Long Parliament,</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb. 3. 1640.</head>
               <p>ALthough we are most unworthy of so rich a mercy; yet having found favour in the eyes of our Dear Lord Jesus, to be kept (even by himself) <hi>from this hour of temptation
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119051:6"/>which is come upon all the world,
<note place="margin">Rev. 3.10. The Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus is wont to keep them in all ages, that keep the word of <hi>His Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
                     </note> to try them that dwell upon the Earth:</hi> we cannot be altogether silent in such a time as this; but desiring to come forth, in the <hi>Name and fear of the Lord,</hi> to plead that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Cause, which by the Army, and their late General, was once frequently dignified with the title of <hi>Honourable, Blessed,</hi> and <hi>Glorious;</hi> we do hope for some measure of Divine Assistance in our <hi>sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, asserting,</hi> and <hi>pleading</hi> for it, as the most noble and excellent Cause, extant in the world at this day: for it is worthy of no less Appellation, then the <hi>Cause of God, of Christ, of his People,</hi> and of the <hi>Inslaved groaning Creatures,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.19.</note> waiting for the manifesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sons of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, that we may, with best advantage to that Cause, bring forth what the Lord hath been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in unto us from <hi>year</hi> to <hi>year,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Retrospection and conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, very useful toward the stating of the Good old Cause.</note> from <hi>Revolution</hi> to <hi>Revolution,</hi> we must (in the Spirit of our minds) <hi>look back</hi> and <hi>consider</hi> the wonderful things which have been done under the Sun, in the sight of this and the neighbour-Nations, this last twenty years, or thereabouts. And for our encouragement here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<note place="margin">Psal. 111.2.</note> we are told in a certain place, that <hi>the WORKS OF THE LORD are GREAT, sought out of all those that have pleasure therein:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and again, he saith, <hi>HIS WORKS ARE HONOURABLE AND GLORIOUS,</hi> He hath made his <hi>WONDERFUL WORKS to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and again, <hi>He hath shewed his people the POWER OF HIS WORKS, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> that he may give them the Heritage of the Heathen.</hi> Wherefore, let all the <hi>Children of the Free-woman,</hi> who, <hi>by reason of use, have had their senses exercised,</hi> in observing those Things
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119051:6"/>which have come to passe in these daies, Call to minde that state of bondage and oppression,
<note place="margin">Bondage and oppression ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heavy at the beginning of the <hi>Scotish</hi> War.</note> under which the Lords Remnant groaned in the year 1640. crying mightily unto their God for a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous full Redemption: which sad Condition of the true spiritual Church of Jesus Christ, termed (by the Court, the Prelates and their party,) <hi>Puritans, Sectaries, Schismaticks,</hi> and <hi>Brownists,</hi> is set forth fully, though briefly, by the under-Officers and Souldiers of the <hi>English</hi> Army,
<note place="margin">Declarat. of <hi>Muscleb. Aug.</hi> 1. 1650.</note> in their Answer to the <hi>Scotish</hi> Papers; to which we refer the Reader, as to a very choice piece, for his better Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Indeed,
<note place="margin">Earnest &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessant Prayer made by the true spiritual seed, for Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance.</note> most earnest and uncessant prayers were made unto the Lord, for Deliverance from under that Antichristian tyranny and persecution, which was then managed with a very high hand, and very presumptuously, by the late King and his Prelates (particularly by <hi>Laud</hi> and <hi>Wren</hi>) by Pillories, scourgings, imprisonments, &amp;c. while Jesuites, Priests, Drunken debauched Parsons,
<note place="margin">This is a known Truth.</note> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars and Curates, were connived at, tolerated, yea countenanced at a very high rate.</p>
               <p>It is of very great concernment also, to call to minde the lively and couragious Spirit that this persecuted and reproached people were filled withall, in beleeving,
<note place="margin">A sparkling Spirit of cheerfulness, (through Faith) a little before Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance.</note> notwithstanding all the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours used by their proud and potent Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to weary them out, and to rid the land of them, if it had been possible.</p>
               <p>And,
<note place="margin">The first stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the best <hi>Scots,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased the Saints hopes in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note> when the best Ministers and people in <hi>Scocland,</hi> did suddenly betake themselves to Arms, upon occasion of the new Service-Book and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119051:7"/>imposed upon them, from the King and his Lord Bishops in <hi>England;</hi> oh how did the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Remnant here, begin to look up, and to lift up their heads,
<note place="margin">Luk. 21.8.</note> with hope that their Redemption was drawing very neer!</p>
               <p>And therefore,
<note place="margin">The Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion House sit after the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament is dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved: this was murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at by all well-affected people.</note> although the King permitted the Convocation-house (after the short Parliament was Dissolved by him in 1640.) to sit and make new Canons; and amongst others, the Oath <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with an intent thereby to engage all leading men in the Nation, never to endeavour, or give their consent, directly, or indirectly, for the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing of Episcopacy,
<note place="margin">Episcopacy begins to stink in all mens nostrils, (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept interessed men).</note> and its train of Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, Deans and Chapters, Rural Deans, &amp;c. Nevertheless, they were so far from obtaining their end in the establishment of their Prelatical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and power; as that now the generality of the vulgar people began to abhor them and their Domination;
<note place="margin">The vulgar people begin to shew rage against the proud Lord Bishops.</note> yea, the very rude Souldiers, which were levied by the King and the Bishops, to settle their Power and Service-Book in <hi>Scotland;</hi> fell foul upon their high Altars, and affronted the Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical Clergy,
<note place="margin">The rude Souldiers also.</note> in many places, as they marched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Rendezvous; which still wonderfully rejoyced the Puritans,
<note place="margin">The praying Puritans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce.</note> Brownists, and Sectaries, as they were still called by the Prelates and their Abettors.</p>
               <p>We who do well know and remember these things,
<note place="margin">Bless the Lord for such a day.</note> do declare to the Glory of our God, at this day, that our hearts and spirits were unspeakably refreshed and comforted, in the observations of the <hi>footsteps of his Providence,</hi> towards his own
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119051:7"/>people, and against his and their enraged Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries, the hour of whose visitation (and utter dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution) did make more then ordinary hast upon them. For,
<note place="margin">The Bishops going about to remedy these mischiefs threatning their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded in all their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels.</note> notwithstanding all the politick plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and combinations of the Court-party, and the Prelats, (who were professed States-men, and ruled the Nation under their Master, by a most Arbitrary power, managed by a most insolent and imperious spirit, intending to suppress the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, and indeed all others that were engaged for the publick good in all the Kings Dominions): The Lord so ordered it, that they were confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in all their Counsels; and the King their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, compelled to call another Parliament, about the space of six moneths after he had so hastily dissolved that before mentioned. Which,
<note place="margin">The Long Parliament is called about half a year af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the other was dissolved</note> because they could not be legally dissolved without their own consent, and continuing their Sessions above 12. years, (the Lord having much work to do by them as Instruments in his hand) are for Distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction sake from others, still called the <hi>LONG PARLIAMENT.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Assembly, being thus called together, in such a juncture of Affairs,
<note place="margin">Not such a time for Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and high spirits since Q. <hi>Maries</hi> time, that I can call to minde.</note> as the like had not been (in several respects) in an hundred years before; were surrounded with very great difficulties, at their first sitting down, the 3. <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1640.</p>
               <p>The Kirk and Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> in high dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content with the King and the <hi>English</hi> Bishops, because of the late violent Proceedings against them.</p>
               <p>A great <hi>Scotish</hi> Army to be paid off; a charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>English</hi> Army to be paid and disbanded, which quartered in the Northern parts of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119051:8"/>
               <p>The proud Prelates both of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> full of the desperate spirit of revenge for the Affronts put upon them every where; bearing themselves high and bold upon the Authority of the King.
<note place="margin">The Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> a great support to Monarchy and Prelacy.</note> Dangerous Counsels and prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in <hi>Ireland,</hi> under the Government of the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> a great Assertor of Arbitrary power, and subverter of those lawes which were the Subjects Buckler and bulwark against Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and oppression; partly by his power, as Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland;</hi> partly by his policy, being a Privy Counsellor. Nevertheless the better part of the House of Commons, with some few in the House of Peers,
<note place="margin">The Long Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament have a glorious A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</note> having an Anointing upon them from the Lord, and couragiously encountring, in the power of that Anointing, with all these, and many other Difficulties, judged almost insupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they overcame them all at length, to the amazement of their friends and foes in all parts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>A brief Account of those principal good Acts of Justice, Equity, and Mercy, whereby the Long Parliament did arrive to a very great height of reputation among all sorts of well-affected people, from their first sitting down, to the beginning of the bloudy Conflict betwixt them and the late King; worthy to be recorded at large, in an Accurate History, to future Ages.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrst, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> their <hi>proclaiming Liberty to the Captives and Exiles;</hi> their opening of the prison-doors to their suffering Countreymen, who had been, by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119051:8"/>the Prelats, and their Faction at Court, pillored,
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Burton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Prynne,</hi> Doctor <hi>Bast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, John Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn,</hi> released and dischar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of Joy from all lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice.</note> stigmatized, scourged, imprisoned, banished, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached, and otherwise oppressed, contrary unto the righteous Laws of God, and of the Land; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, for their Faithful testimony, against the superstitious Innovations of the Lord Bishops: which Act of the Parliament, was resented and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged with the highest satisfaction, and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation of the best people of the Land, that could be well imagined.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Their <hi>Impeachment of some principall Ministers of State,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Strafford, Laud,</hi> Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> and others.</note> (who were the chief Instruments of Tyranny and oppression) as guilty of high Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son; whom accordingly they prosecuted with a most noble Spirit of courage and high resolution; until they brought them to condign punishment, for their Treasons, and other high crimes and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors, in the open sight of all men.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, their <hi>owning, countenancing, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging, those Non-conformists,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters come out of their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners where they had been hid; and look Episcopacy in the face with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fear.</note> both Ministers and People, who during the Reign of King <hi>James,</hi> and of King <hi>Charles,</hi> had been silenced, degraded, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived, persecuted, and otherwise abused by the Prelats.</p>
               <p>It would have done a <hi>good mans heart good indeed,</hi> to have seen Ancient Preachers, and other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, appear in publick, without danger, after so many years obscuring themselves from the knowledge of men, because of the rage of the Prelats and their Pursevants, watching alwaies an opportunity to catch and crush them; who now, were instrumental several waies, to undermine the Prelats and their <hi>Rable of Romish Ceremonies,</hi> and that publickly, and to purpose.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119051:9"/>
               <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Their <hi>setting a sharp edge upon those Laws,</hi> which had been made against Priests, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites, and other <hi>Romish</hi> Recusants; who by means of the <hi>Queens,
<note place="margin">Papists afraid.</note> Lauds, Cottingtons,</hi> and Secretary <hi>Windebanks</hi> Interest, were grown very insolent and daring, in this Nation; but now began to hide their heads.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Their <hi>Damning that illegal Imposition of Ship-money,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ship-money drown'd.</note> and relieving such worthy Patriots as were imprisoned, and otherwise abused for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing to submit to that Arbitrary Tax. Questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and punishing those Judges also,
<note place="margin">Corrupt Judges im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached.</note> who, by their suffrage, had strengthened the hands of the King, and of his Councell, in these and other waies of unrighteous usurpation.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Their <hi>suppressing, and utterly destroying those Arbitrary oppressive Courts,
<note place="margin">High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission Court, Star-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, new Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy'd.</note> Oathes, Supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Customs, Canons, and Constitutions Ecclesiastical;</hi> which were a snare, and a wonderful terror to the good and free People of the Nation, every where.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Their <hi>turning the Lords Spiritual out of doors,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> from the House of Peers, namely, the Lords Archbishops,
<note place="margin">Prelats sent packing out of doors, with their Rochets and Tippets.</note> and Lords Bishops, who were bold enough, (even to impudency) on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of their own Prelatical Interest; but great obstructors of any motions for the relief of the poor Puritans, oppressed by their Hierarchy: which disgraceful expulsion, they pull'd upon themselves, by their presumptuous Protestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons against all proceeding that should pass in their absence; pretending they were affrighted by the <hi>Londoners</hi> coming to <hi>Westminster,</hi> to call for Justice upon those who were Traitors to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119051:9"/>the true Interest of the good People.</p>
               <p>These, and many other memorable Actions thus managed, by this <hi>generous and Heroick Spirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Court-party, and Pontifical Clergy enra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to finde their usurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions opposed by their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical subjects.</note> (which then appeared to animate and Actuate the House of Commons) did put the King, the Queen, the Papists, the Prelats, the Hectors of the Court, and other sons of Belial, into <hi>outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Passions</hi> of vexation of spirit, wrath, revenge, and great hatred; resolving, if it were possible, to put a Check upon that <hi>popular Spirit,</hi> for the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of his <hi>Monarchical Prerogative,</hi> against this threatned Inundation: which purpose of his, was brought to light,
<note place="margin">The Five Members in great danger to be surpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</note> by that first <hi>extravagant march</hi> of his, into the House of Commons, with armed Cavaliers at his heels, to lay violent hands upon some of their number, ere they were a ware: from which signal Circumstance,
<note place="margin">Manifest sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes of the Dissolution of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> the most intelligent By-standers did rationally conclude, that a very high and sharp contest, betwixt the King and the Parliament, was even at the door.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:119051:10"/>
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>The King and Parliament disagree about Breach of priviledges, in the case of the Five Members. The</hi> Londoners <hi>own the Parliament, against the King in that matter. The face of a Civil War. The Cause is stated. Armies raised. A Scotch Army brought in upon the Account of a Solemn League. Some godly persons scruple the taking of it. This kindles a fire in the Parliaments Quarters. Their Cause brought low. Prayer made in these streights by an hidden People.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Five Members being sheltered in the City of <hi>London,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Five Members shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, against the King.</note> out of the Kings reach, and after a few daies, put into their places by strong hand, <hi>in contradiction to the King,</hi> and that his desperate Design;
<note place="margin">Brought in triumph to the Parliament, in Affront to all the Kings Power.</note> He discerned an impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to destroy them, by any assistance near at hand: Whereupon, <hi>forsaking White-hall,</hi> and pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing by degrees to the City of <hi>York,</hi> did by and by, betake himself to Arms: Whereupon, it came to pass,
<note place="margin">He being thus bearded by his subjects, makes haste in fear from <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall.</hi>
                  </note> that a most expensive, bloudy War was Commenced and violently carried on, betwixt the King and Parliament, for divers years; which occasioned a stating of the Cause on both Hands;
<note place="margin">War com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menc'd, the Cause stated on both sides.</note> Both Parties endeavouring to insinuate and infuse into the People of the Nation, the Justice of their Cause, each of them according to their proper Interest.</p>
               <p>The Parliament, stating their Cause with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the true Interest of the people, did so express themselves, as that we understood their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119051:10"/>full purpose was, to recover and secure the Just Liberty, safety and happiness of the well-affected of the Nation: So, as that they might not be <hi>swallowed up in the Gulf of Monarchical Prerogative</hi> and Arbitrary power, any more for ever; as they had been endangered, for many years before. And, the better to effect the matter,
<note place="margin">The Magazine at <hi>Hull</hi> seized by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> seized the Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine at <hi>Hull;</hi> Declared for the true Protestant Religion, the Laws of the Land, Priviledges of Parliament, and Liberties of the People; not excluding at the same time,
<note place="margin">The Parliament did not at the beginning Declare against the King, but Orders were given forth in the name of King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</note> the Person and just Prerogative of the King; affirming frequently, they were not only willing, but Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to make him a more Glorious Prince, then any of his Predecessors, if he would comply, and hearken to their Counsel.
<note place="margin">They had no thoughts at the first, to ruine him and his Family, But the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel of God takes place, not their Counsel.</note> So far were they from any purposes to destroy Him and his Family at that time, and many years after: although in process of time, it came to pass, by the Determinate Counsel and fore-knowledge of God, beyond their own Intentions or expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>The King (and his evil Counsel) likewise, the better to engage his Subjects, set up his Standard, and stated the Cause, even in the self-same words (for it was esteemed his proper interest also in that Juncture): stamping upon his new Coyn, <hi>For the Protestant Religion,</hi> the <hi>Lawes of England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Both Parties make their appeal to God, and to the People.</note> and the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of Parliament:</hi> this <hi>superadded Circumstance,</hi> from both parties was observed, <hi>viz.</hi> their <hi>making solemn Appeals</hi> to God, and to the People, to judge betwixt them.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119051:11"/>
               <p>The generality of the Puritans and Sectaries,
<note place="margin">The Puritans of all sorts, &amp; all who had groaned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der oppression, cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e to the Parliament.</note> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with other honest and well-affected of the Nation, beleeving the Declarations and Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strances of the Parliament, ingage themselves to strengthen their hands in this Noble Cause so sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and declared,
<note place="margin">And bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all kindes of Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> with all sorts of Contributions; and, which was the life of all, with Faith, Spirit, and Courage, in abundance.</p>
               <p>The Papists,
<note place="margin">The Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents. The Royal and Prelarical party come in to the King.</note> the Prelats, and all Cathedral men, the Chancellors, Surrogates, Archdeacons, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritors, with all that depend upon the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, a great part of the Nobility, the debauched Gentry, many of the Commons, give credit to the King, and cry him up, as ingaged in a most righteous Cause;
<note place="margin">The Puritans and all that joyned in the Parliaments Cause, are now frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called Roundheads and Rebels.</note> bidding the people take no care; the Roundheads (as now they were called, the word Puritan growing out of date) shall never prevail against <hi>the Lords Anointed:</hi> no question but the King shall prevail against all his Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. And the truth is, if by <hi>hellish oathes and curses,</hi> if by <hi>horrid blasphemies and outragious threatnings,</hi> what they would do to the <hi>confusion of the Round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads,</hi> they could have overcome them; they were the only men of war, alive, meet to fight the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels of their soveraign Lord the King.</p>
               <p>But to proceed:
<note place="margin">Souldiers of Fortune on both sides.</note> both Armies being filled up with Commanders from forein parts, the War was drawn out after the manner of Mercenaries. The <hi>Scotish</hi> Covenanters in a short time are by Treaty brought in upon the terms of taking a so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant,
<note place="margin">The solemn League enters <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note> enter <hi>England</hi> in the Parliaments Cause, against their own Native Prince. The Issue was doubtful, Treaties were fruitless; the Northern and Western parts were
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119051:11"/>possessed by the Kings Forces, after several Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tails, Skirmishes, Sieges. At length, the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Army,</hi> under the Earl of <hi>Essex</hi> is taken in a share in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and the <hi>Parliament Cause and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest</hi> appeareth at a very great loss, which was the occasion of <hi>hellish Blasphemies</hi> among the <hi>Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers,</hi> both in the English and Latine Language: For,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>It was magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied when it came into <hi>England</hi> first, as the very Ark of Gods presence.</p>
                     <p>And many were perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded we should prosper upon the Account of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
                     <p>Divers ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>se to take it, and thereupon lose their Trusts.</p>
                  </note> notwithstanding the assistance of the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant, (the great Idol of both Kingdoms,</hi> at that time,) the affairs of the Parliament were at so low an ebb, by the concurrent force of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Causes, that many good Men did begin so far to despair of victory, or salvation, that they were transporting themselves on the other side the water. And now, what some few, precious hearts did foresee, did accordingly come to pass; namely, that the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi> would not be found a <hi>fit weapon in this warfare:</hi> &amp; therefore, could never be perswaded to enter into it, or to suffer it to enter into them. Although Order upon Order issued forth, from the <hi>Scotish Spirit</hi> in <hi>English-men,</hi> to constrain all the Commanders and Officers, to submit unto it, or otherwise to quit their places and trust in this Common Cause.</p>
               <p>This new Intestine contest among the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarians, riseth high:
<note place="margin">Division be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters and the Non-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters.</note> Will you not take the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant? all the good wise men of the <hi>Kirk of Scotland have taken it:</hi> their <hi>best Ministers,</hi> their <hi>chief Elders;</hi> and the <hi>good wise men of both Houses of Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Reverend Assembly of Divines,</hi> they have all taken it, and it doth very well with them all;
<note place="margin">Uniformity pressed.</note> they are presently better upon the taking of it: more zealous, more trusty, more capable; Nay, your own party, the <hi>Heads of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119051:12"/>Congregational way,</hi> say it may be taken very safely, without any danger at all.
<note place="margin">Uniformity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected.</note> It is answered by the Sectaries, (but, they are very conscientious ones), We cannot take it, we dare not take it; <hi>we desire the Liberty of our Consciences,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists glad of the Division.</note> &amp;c. Now the difference betwixt <hi>the Presbyterians and the Dissenting Brethren</hi> breaks out into a flame; and the Kings party being quick of apprehension, do presently begin to warm themselves at that Fire.</p>
               <p>The firm <hi>Covenanters, both Scotish, and English,</hi> they are now the only Orthodox Divines, and the sound Protestants; In contradistinction to the <hi>Cavaliers on the one hand,</hi> and the <hi>Sectaries on the other.</hi> But the Sectaries, that will not take the Covenant, they must be discountenanced.
<note place="margin">Sectaries dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanced.</note> Divers eminent men among them are laid aside, Division aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; this poor people that desire <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tormented with a strange Gangrena.</note> are hugely <hi>tormented</hi> with a <hi>cruel Gangrena,</hi> (a Book so called) whereby they are rendred so far as ill-will, and lies, and slanders, and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitings can prevail, a <hi>very monstrous people:</hi> all kennels are raked, for dirt, to throw in their faces; they are not worthy to come neer the houses,
<note place="margin">Note this well.</note> or be in the neighbourhood and company of the <hi>Orthodox;</hi> so that the <hi>poor Independents,</hi> and other good men, Non-conformists to the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>(as the Presbyters were formerly, Non-conformists to the Prelats)</hi> are exceedingly slighted and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Nevertheless, some of them, by the means of some <hi>moderate and prudent men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Some of the best Sectaries connived at, by means of moderate men</note> are continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Imployment, because of their <hi>Abilities and Activity against the common Enemy,</hi> and for the <hi>true Interest</hi> of the <hi>English</hi> Nation.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119051:12"/>
               <p>However, the Cause was given for almost lost by those, who being <hi>of a weak Faith,</hi> had thoughts of retirement.
<note place="margin">Many of a weak faith were ready to give all for lost</note> Despondencies appeared every where (for a little space) because of Divisions in the Parliament, Army, Assembly, City, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this interim, there were a hidden People that plyed the throne of Grace, pleaded our Cause, there at that throne,
<note place="margin">An hidden choice People had recourse to Prayers.</note> with all Scripture-Arguments, <hi>the Glory of God, the promised Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his People; the insolency and blasphemy of the Adversary, if he should prevail after so many bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels and appeals; the increase of bondage and perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution after victory on the Kings side; the Prophesies,</hi> concerning the <hi>destruction of Antichrist, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness of God,</hi> for the finishing of what he had begun, our being taken as <hi>firebrands out of the burning,</hi> but the other day, as it were, and will the Lord throw us in again? These pleadings and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postulations were not known publickly; but it was <hi>given us to believe</hi> that the work should prosper, though there were at present a dismal death upon it, and many had <hi>joy and peace in so believing, blessed be the Name of our God and Father, for ever and ever, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119051:13"/>
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>The new Model brought forth in a needfull season, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes wonderfull victorious. The King goes in a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guise to the Scotish Army. They deliver him up to the Parliaments Commissioners at</hi> New-Castle. <hi>Brought prisoner to</hi> Holmby-<hi>House: afterward the Army, upon Disgust given from the Parliament, take him into their custody, and treat upon terms. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward prisoner in the Isle of</hi> Wight: <hi>a second Warre. That is ended with successe also, to the Sectaries. At length it's resolved to bring the King to a Tryal for his life.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALl on a sudden, while the <hi>Affaires of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> are so <hi>perplexed,</hi> and <hi>upon a Precipice,</hi> within a step of ruine, behold, there appeareth a <hi>New Model'd Army,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The new Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del.</note> notwithstanding all the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Difficulties, Discouragements, and Disad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages; but how doth it appear? <hi>A foolish thing, a weak thing, one of the despised things of this World.</hi> For now the <hi>Covenanters</hi> and the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> agreed against this <hi>unexpected appearance</hi> of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence on the behalf of the true seed;
<note place="margin">It's account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and called by Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiers, The new Noddle.</note> they both call'd it in scorn, The <hi>new Noddle,</hi> the <hi>Common By-word of the Carnal seed,</hi> both in the Kings and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Quarters.
<note place="margin">The Sectaries own it a fruit of prayer.</note> But many honest hearts, being perswaded that it was the product of Faith and Prayer, <hi>had joy and peace in believing</hi> (as was said even now) that the Lord would make use of it; and the rather, because, it was so exceedingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spised in the eyes of those that <hi>magnified</hi> the <hi>solemne League</hi> and <hi>Covenant;</hi> which after a short space of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119051:13"/>time, began apparently to abate of its <hi>Lordlinesse</hi> and <hi>Imposing Spirit,</hi> to the great ease of many good hearts, especially such,
<note place="margin">The Interest of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Interest of Christ, distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished.</note> as began betimes to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish, betwixt the <hi>Interest of the Kirk of</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and the <hi>true Interest of Jesus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For while both the <hi>Covenanters</hi> and <hi>Cavaliers</hi> were <hi>scofsing</hi> at this <hi>new Model,</hi> and expecting a sudden destruction to overtake it, upon a distinct account; (these, by reason the <hi>old experienced Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders</hi> were either layed aside, or had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn themselves, except Major General <hi>Skippon,</hi> who (in this desperate Paroxysme) had been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Instrumental in the forming this <hi>new Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia:</hi> those, because it was so full of <hi>Sectaries</hi> and Enemies to the <hi>solemne League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi>) behold,
<note place="margin">A glorious vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory given to the new Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del.</note>
                  <hi>a very glorious Victory</hi> did (sudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wonderfully) fall as it were into their laps, from the hand of the <hi>Lord of Hosts;</hi> which being seconded and followed, with a continued series of extraordinary successes,
<note place="margin">The Mockers amazed.</note> to the <hi>Amazement</hi> of <hi>the mockers,</hi> now become more serious and sad; the <hi>solemne League and Covenant</hi> became at last, <hi>a very Cheap Thing,</hi> allover <hi>England,</hi> and was no longer <hi>adored as a Goddess,</hi> by the Parliament,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant lamented by the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, &amp; sleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries.</p>
                     <p>The new Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del bears the Kings Forces every where.</p>
                  </note> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foretime; onely, the <hi>Engaged, Orthodox Divines</hi> and their admirers, made great Lamentation over it, for a long season, even till the death of the late King, and some time after.</p>
               <p>But to passe on: when all the <hi>Kings field-Forces were beaten,</hi> his <hi>Garisons surrendred</hi> for the most part, <hi>Oxford,</hi> his <hi>Head-Quarters</hi> (where was his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal Residence) <hi>beaten up;</hi> and the <hi>Controversie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Cause and Cause,</hi> so farre decided, after so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny solemne and bloudy Appeals on both sides; He
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119051:14"/>disguises himself,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>The King gets out of <hi>Oxford</hi> by stealth. Goes to the <hi>Scots</hi> in by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paths.</p>
                     <p>They deliver up the King at <hi>New-Castle,</hi> and are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive 200000 pound.</p>
                  </note> and with one or two in Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, conveyes himself through the dark, and in by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paths, to the <hi>Scots Covenanters</hi> at the Siege of <hi>Newwark;</hi> who, marching with him to <hi>New-Castle,</hi> make a very good Market of him, selling his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, in effect, for 200000 pound, and for quitting <hi>England;</hi> the King delivered up, carried Captive, and Imprisoned in <hi>Holmby</hi> House, <hi>Northampton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stire.</hi> Any one may imagine now, that the <hi>Scots Covenanters</hi> were Odious and Abominable to the <hi>Cavaliers of the right stamp;</hi> calling them <hi>Judasses,</hi> onely they sold, say they, their Master for a greater price then He did his, so long ago.</p>
               <p>It may be easily conceived,
<note place="margin">The Lambs of Christ leap for joy.</note> how all those <hi>Lambs of Christ,</hi> that before the War, had been <hi>worried by the Prelates,</hi> under the Countenance and protection of this unhappy Prince (now taken Captive) did leap and skip for joy, that the <hi>beasts of prey</hi> were thus subdued and recompenced before their eyes. Now was <hi>Joy in the Tabernacles of the Righteous;</hi> and how did they <hi>eat their meat with gladnesse and single<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of heart,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.46.</note> praising God, and having favour with all the people,</hi> that did Cordially adhere to the Cause of Freedom and Righteousnesse, now so prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in the Nations! the certain knowledge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of those works of wonder, are very sweet at this day, to many hundreds.</p>
               <p>But in processe of time,
<note place="margin">The spirit of the solemne League dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased, and Plot the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding of the Army. 1647.</note> the <hi>Spirit of the League</hi> (aforesaid) did again bestirre it self so far in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> particularly in the Houses of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and among the Orthordox Divines, that the Cause was exceedingly endangered the second time.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119051:14"/>
               <p>For the <hi>new Moddel</hi> should have been <hi>immediately disbanded,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The new Moddel to be disbanded, are a ware of the Plot.</note> upon pretence there was no visible Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and so, no need of a <hi>standing Army:</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other was to be formed of a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> make, to keep down the Royal party. <hi>Skippon</hi> was to draw a part into <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. Colonel <hi>Graves,</hi> having private Orders to convey the King suddenly to the Parliament, to Head the <hi>Presbyterian party</hi> against the <hi>new Moddel:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The King sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly taken out of <hi>Holmby</hi> House, and brought into the Armies Quarters.</note> but Cornet <hi>Joyce</hi> was an instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at that time, to prevent that dreadfull Relapse into Bondage, under the solemne League-men; which was more feared and hated by the <hi>Children of the Free-woman,</hi> then death it self.</p>
               <p>After the <hi>new Moddel</hi> had thus gotten the King into their possession, so that the <hi>solemne League-men</hi> both <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>English</hi> were thus disappointed (as it were by a most wonderfull interposition from Heaven) they, according to that principle, which was held and owned by them,
<note place="margin">The King hath Liberty of Conscience granted him by the Army.</note> were willing the King should have the <hi>Liberty of his Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> and thereupon permitted him to enjoy his own Chaplains, and some friends, the sight of his Children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he had not obtained before. This wrought in the King, an Apprehension that his state was better'd, by the late change. Inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he had rather be a Prisoner to the <hi>new Moddel,</hi> then to the <hi>solemne League and Covenant,</hi> as finding fairer Quarter.</p>
               <p>But now was the hour of temptation upon the <hi>new Moddel:</hi> for the King,
<note place="margin">An hour of temptation upon the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, by the Kings compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny among them.</note> with his friends about him, insinuating himself into some <hi>Leaders of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> had prevailed with them so far, that they began to <hi>Tamper</hi> and <hi>Trinkle</hi> with him about his Return and Restitution, in Freedom, safety and honour;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119051:15"/>so that the fears of some <hi>choice Christians</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, lest some mischief might befall the Cause and Them, by means of that <hi>carnal and worldly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance</hi> with such an <hi>Arch-enemy of Jesus Christ,</hi> guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of so much bloud and persecutions: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon made their <hi>prayers unto God, that their feet might not be taken in that snare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Issue of all which noise and danger, about the bringing home the King in the <hi>Freedom and pomp aforesaid,</hi> with his Queen and Children, was his sudden flight into the <hi>Isle of Wight:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The King in the <hi>Isle of Wight.</hi> A second War</note> where he remaining <hi>firm</hi> to his own <hi>Regal Interest,</hi> did by degrees (though in prison) raise a <hi>second War</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding dangerous, by Commission given to his Son the Prince; whereupon followed the Revolt of the Navy, the Revolt of <hi>Wales,</hi> the Insurrection in <hi>Kent,</hi> the <hi>Scotish</hi> Invasion under Duke <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> &amp;c. several Tumults and Risings in and about the City: all which happening, as it were at once, the Army had their hands full in all places: not to mention his Commission to <hi>Ormond,</hi> and the <hi>Irish,</hi> about the same time. Insomuch, that it is ascribed to the <hi>especial loving kindness of the Lord,</hi> that those of his People which continued faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and unshaken in this day, had not been utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly overwhelmed by the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Covenanters</hi> in <hi>Conjunction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">King and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters joyn in the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond War.</note> in this Juncture likewise.</p>
               <p>And therefore let us now remember, with a mixture of Joy and wonder, that although the <hi>publick Cause</hi> after several <hi>considerable Advances,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The publick Cause in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger again.</note> and sometimes by <hi>fraud</hi> even ready to expire and breath its last; yet by unexpected and secret operations of <hi>Divine Counsel,</hi> it did as often revive, and regain its former (yea
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119051:15"/>greater) strength and beauty, to the joyful <hi>obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of all its Advocates,</hi> and <hi>great indignation of its Adversaries.</hi> Which assertion was made evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, with a witness, in a short time, after the <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond War</hi> was happily waded through: for now the <hi>New Model,</hi> having been warned, by the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of their <hi>former tampering</hi> with the King; and having (before they had any courage to ingage in the <hi>second War</hi> aforesaid) <hi>humbled themselves before the Lord</hi> for three daies together,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>The Army humbled and ashamed for their tampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with the King.</p>
                     <p>See St <hi>Albans</hi> Declaration. See <hi>Allen</hi>'s Memorial.</p>
                     <p>They resolve to bring him to Justice.</p>
                  </note>
                  <hi>waiting at his foot</hi> (before their march into the field) <hi>for counsel and blessing,</hi> did come at last to such a result, (Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; Ingagement) among themselves at <hi>Windsor-Castle,</hi> as that the <hi>Cause</hi> seemed now to be a <hi>New Cause,</hi> or, the Former <hi>raised in glory.</hi> For now, it is resolved that the <hi>King is a man of bloud,</hi> and <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Son of Death:</hi> that if ever the Lord conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scend <hi>to go forth with their Armies,</hi> and prosper their enterprise, they would certainly endeavour to do Justice upon him, as a person, who, according to the Law of God, <hi>must die the Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And upon this <hi>Advance of the Cause,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>The Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Generally discontented at the noise of trying the King for his life.</p>
                     <p>The Solemn League dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, when the King was dismem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred.</p>
                  </note> we doe reckon the <hi>Generality of the Covenanters fell off,</hi> and were left behinde: for then there was a principal Clause in the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi> torn in pieces; <hi>The honour and power of the King,</hi> being ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly and for ever Abolished and Disannulled: see it pleaded in the Armies Remonstrance from St <hi>Albans,</hi> in these words, Proposal the first:
<q>That that Capital and grand Author of our troubles, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the late King, by whose Commissions, Commands, or procurement; and in whose behalf, and from whose interest (only) of will and power, all our wars and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles have been, (with all the miseries attending them)
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119051:16"/>may be speedily brought to Justice, for the Treasons, bloud and mischief, he is therein guilty of.</q>
               </p>
               <p>It is to be remembred,
<note place="margin">The personal Treaty dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to the whole Cause.</note> that at this very time, the Parliament was treating with the King at the Isle of <hi>Wight,</hi> by their Commissioners, for his return in safety, freedom and honour: and had not the Army seconded their Proposition aforesaid,
<note place="margin">The March to <hi>Westminster</hi> for secluding the corrupt Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</note> by an immediate and swift March from St. <hi>Albans</hi> to <hi>Westminster,</hi> the <hi>whole Cause</hi> in humane probability had been again lost; which the <hi>new Moddel</hi> had now twice rescued and recovered for themselves and the best-affected people to the Cause of Christ, out of the hands of the Cavaliers and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters,
<note place="margin">Hosea 14.9.</note> with wonderful success. <hi>Who is wise, and he shall understand these things; prudent, and he shall know them? for the waies of the Lord are right, and the just shall walk in them; but the transgressors shall fall therein.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Scotish</hi> and <hi>English</hi> Covenanted, troubled for the King.</note> The <hi>angry Spirit</hi> of <hi>high Presbytery</hi> stirs again; for now the <hi>publick Cause</hi> prospering and prevailing above and beyond the <hi>Scotish Interest</hi> in this Nation, the <hi>Solemn League</hi>-Men are become now again, a very <hi>peevish Generation,</hi> not enduring the <hi>product</hi> of their <hi>own Sermons and Papers:</hi> for how many hundreds, yea, thousands of ear and eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witnesses are there, that can testifie how bitterly <hi>Meroz was cursed</hi> by them,
<note place="margin">Judg. 5.23.</note>
                  <hi>for not coming to the help of the Lord,
<note place="margin">The Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Text tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon them, for tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning head up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, after they had stir'd up the people by it, against their King.</note> to the help of the Lord against the Mighty?</hi> and now that the Lord was helped against the Mighty, (the high and mighty being brought down from their Seats) what <hi>frowardness of Spirit</hi> did break forth from those <hi>principal Preachers,</hi> which in the beginning of the war, stirred up the people to fight against the King! But the sentence against the evil work, and the evil worker is exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119051:16"/>at length, the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant notwithstanding,</hi> and notwithstanding all their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, now all too late, and all too weak, to save him whom they <hi>had formerly prayed against:</hi> (for many mens <hi>prayers alter</hi> with their <hi>worldly Interest,</hi> and so do their <hi>preachings</hi> also, whereby they undermine the reputation of their own doctrines &amp; Integrity,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.4. Monarchy laid aside.</note> and <hi>Consult shame to their own Ministry</hi>) <hi>but let God be glorified, and every man a lyar.</hi> This <hi>unhappy King,</hi> being so cut off, as appears by the Judgment, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, Sentence and Execution upon Record, for this and the next Generation to gaze upon,
<note place="margin">A Republick introduced.</note> with pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions sutable to their different principles) the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is changed from Monarchy to a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth;</hi> and an Ingagement imposed upon all, to submit to the present Power, who expect protection by it: fair promises were made, by the <hi>remaining part</hi> of the <hi>Long-Parliament,</hi> how happy a people we should appear to be, under them and the <hi>Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the Liberties of England;</hi> as may be seen in their <hi>publick Papers</hi> at that day.</p>
               <p>But verily, <hi>if poor men be vanity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 62.9.</note> we are sure <hi>great men are a lye:</hi> and they themselves (if Ingenuity be permitted to speak freely in their Breasts) will confess,
<note place="margin">But not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted in any proportion to promises and expectations.</note> they <hi>answered not the minde of the Lord</hi> in any proportion to all those signs and wonders which they were witnesses unto, during the blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy contest betwixt their inraged Adversaries and themselves. There were, indeed, a Generation of Ransomed and Redeemed people, <hi>for whose sakes principally the Lord reproved the King and Bishops;</hi> and after them, the carnal Covenanters, who <hi>NOW</hi> began to <hi>state the Cause</hi> according to its <hi>proper worth</hi> and <hi>excellency;</hi> for they being after so great expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119051:17"/>made <hi>wise with the wisdom of God</hi> in some measure, now proceed in a more distinct manner to <hi>try the things that differ, and to approve the things that are most excellent,</hi> as the Apostle exhorts <hi>the Saints at Philippi,
<note place="margin">Phil. 1.10.</note> with the Bishops and Deacons:</hi> and therefore, for the more particular and effectual pleading that which we call <hi>the Glorious Cause,</hi> &amp;c. we must Recapitulate some precedent passages.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V. <hi>A brief Recapitulation of some passages; for the better stating the Controversie betwixt the</hi> Covenanters <hi>and the</hi> Sectaries. <hi>The Covenant differently inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted. The</hi> Scotish <hi>Spirit, in</hi> English <hi>men, blows the coals of Division. The</hi> Sectaries <hi>not willing to be under the power of</hi> Presbytery. <hi>The</hi> Classical Cause <hi>stated in</hi> 7. <hi>Heads. The honest</hi> Sectaries <hi>engrave the</hi> Name of Christ <hi>upon the forehead of their Cause, in seven distinct Propositions: but feigned friends desert it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere was a very fair Gloss put upon the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant at the beginning,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Some Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries took the Covenant in simplicity, not then knowing the grand Design.</note> and many dear Servants of Christ took it <hi>in the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of their hearts,</hi> because it seemed to set up <hi>the word of God as Umpire in the Dispute of Reformation:</hi>
                  <q>the <hi>principal Clause</hi> that satisfied their Spirits, was, a Covenanting to reform in Doctrine, Worship, and Discipline, according to the Word of God, and the example of the best reformed Churches.</q> Which General terms left it under suspence,
<note place="margin">It's Disputed which are the best reformed Churches.</note> and undetermined, <hi>which of the Reformed Churches had attained the highest degree of Reformation:</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:119051:17"/>and their friends judged the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> the <hi>best reformed;</hi> the Dissenting Brethren approved the <hi>Reformation in</hi> New-England <hi>to be the more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent:</hi> but in the common calamity and danger, they did not at the first so openly and particularly as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert each of them their opinions and perswasions, but kept their faith to themselves; and when upon several emergent occasions, <hi>some smoaking firebrands</hi> were cast in amongst them, (by weak or subtle In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments) to set all in a flame, they were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently quenched by the prudence and authority of <hi>some principal men,</hi> (Friends to the Common Cause) as foreseeing the Common Enemy by such Division, would be in a Capacity to destroy them both; and so to <hi>triumph</hi> over the <hi>Covenanters,</hi> as well as over the <hi>Sectaries,</hi> as being inraged against them all. But it is to be remembred also, that the Prebyterians (a little before, and) after the trial and Death of <hi>Charles Steward</hi> the Father, discovering themselves as <hi>passionate well-wishers to Kingship or Monarchy,</hi> for their own Interest,
<note place="margin">The Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters very zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the King after his death.</note> as the Cavaliers (and afterward ventured their lives many of them, for the bringing in young <hi>Charles</hi>) and looking upon themselves, as the elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the Sectaries, <hi>hoped the inheritance should have been theirs;</hi> and therefore, did <hi>state and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate the Cause of Common right and Liberty,</hi> with a very full and favourable aspect upon their <hi>own Classical concernments,</hi> expecting at the Kings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn and compliance, the greatest portion (if not all) of <hi>the blessings of Liberty and Government</hi> both in Church and State, to fall to their share:
<note place="margin">The Sectaries Joynt-purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers with the Presbyters</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though all was purchased, at as great a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of bloud and Treasure, issuing out of the <hi>veins
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119051:18"/>and purses of the Sectaries (consideratis considerandis)</hi> as they themselves had parted with, toward the purchase, as aforesaid.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sectaries</hi> perceiving the <hi>tendency</hi> of such <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> and <hi>Designs,</hi> as now began to appear and operate more openly, then at the beginning, did for some space of time before the Kings death, prepare to distinguish <hi>betwixt Cause and Cause, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Interest and Interest;</hi> and came to this result, that the <hi>well-beloved interest and Cause which the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant did intend to set up and stand by,</hi> was plainly, a <hi>worldly, carnal, selfish Cause and Interest;</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly resolved to undermine and supplant it all they could in a lawful way, without distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of that little breathing, now vouchsafed, upon the death of the late King.</p>
               <p>The Cause (that is, the Cause Ecclesiastical) stated and owned by the Classical Ministers and their Friends, appears to be this.</p>
               <p>In stead of having the <hi>King head of the Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> as he was by Law before the war, they would have the King, but a <hi>Member of the Church,</hi> as it was in <hi>Scotland,</hi> or at the most, but a chief, ruling Lay-Elder.</p>
               <p>In stead of the <hi>old Service-book,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Ordination of Priests and Deacons, Marriages, Visitation of the Sick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A <hi>new invented Directory</hi> must be fram'd, to teach the Clergy how to Preach, Pray, Marry, &amp; visit the sick, according to their vain Inventions.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And whereas heretofore the King, as being head of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> did use to censure any Church-officer and Minister in the Land, in his High Commission Court: now for the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the Classical Cause, it is very meet,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119051:18"/>he himself should be <hi>obnoxious to the stool of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> and any other Censure of the Kirk, as any other Member.</p>
               <p>Again, whereas Church-Government before, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> was by Diocesses, Provinces, Convocations Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal; now there must be a Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by Classes, Provincial Synods, and General Assemblies: both on the backside of the Bible.</p>
               <p>Moreover, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> instead of the Title of Lord Bishops to Govern the Church of <hi>England</hi> in state, now turned out of their Chairs, by these supplanters, they will be content with the Honour of Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: Sir <hi>John</hi> Presbyter shall serve the turn, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of my Lord Bishop. We mean, the outward, worldly honour of <hi>High-Presbytery</hi> must be a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree below that honour which the late <hi>Lords spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> did possesse: a <hi>Knight spiritual</hi> is to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to stand one step lower, then a <hi>Lord spiritual,</hi> in all <hi>National Churches,</hi> where such worldly honour doth prevail.</p>
               <p>Instead of the Bishops Lands, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> which were sold for the further carrying on the Common-Cause a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Prelates and the King, as the head of them, to the prejudice of Presbytery, they will be content with the Deans and Chapters Lands, (if they could have gotten them) as sufficient to <hi>bear up that Port and Grandeur,</hi> that will appertain to their <hi>new Dignity and Jurisdiction;</hi> but to sell those Lands away from the <hi>new Church-Governours,</hi> will be <hi>hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Sacrilege,</hi> and very destructive to the cause of high Presbytery.</p>
               <p>And seventhly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> for a Close in <hi>stating this new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest,</hi> the Parish Churches, Parish Dues, Tithes,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119051:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119051:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:119051:20"/>Obventions and Oblations, Easter Books, and other Perquisites, shall be as they were in the dayes of the Lord Bishops their Predecessors; with this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration added, that every one, who will be Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, Vicar, or Curate from this time forth, shall submit to the <hi>new Ordination;</hi> which shall be <hi>as good, to all Interests and purposes, for making them capable of spiritual promotions,</hi> as that which was conferred by any Lord Bishop, or Archbishop of them all. Let the <hi>Churchwarden, Clark,</hi> &amp;c. continue as of old. <hi>Funeral Sermons</hi> and <hi>Marriages,</hi> and all the <hi>Parish-Fees</hi> must not be diminished; and the <hi>Parish-Church,</hi> and not go astray under pain of Church-censure, to be inflicted according to the <hi>new Classical Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I apprehend this to be the <hi>summe</hi> and <hi>Quintes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence</hi> of the <hi>Covenanters Cause,</hi> which they desired to promote in both Nations, in opposition to the <hi>Lord Bishops, on one hand, and the poor Sectaries on the other.</hi> Esteeming <hi>Prelacy</hi> the <hi>Centre of Superstition,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Independency</hi> the <hi>sink of Schisne;</hi> but their own <hi>Model</hi> must be the <hi>Mirror of Reformation.</hi> Now whether it be not stated aright, and (if it be,) whether it doth not appear to the seeing eye of equal Judges, a <hi>poor, low, carnal Cause,</hi> let any man that will, freely declare his minde.</p>
               <p>But however, we may be mistaken in stating and judging of it; many of the Choice followers of the Lamb, found cause to disown <hi>Scotish Presbytery,</hi> as well as <hi>English Prelacy,</hi> especially in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars before mentioned; and therefore a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and after the Kings death, the <hi>name of the Lord Jesus</hi> is <hi>Ingraven upon the forehead of that Cause,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119051:20"/>which from about that time, began to be, and to appear, as distinct from <hi>that of the Presbytery,</hi> as that of Presbytery, from the <hi>Cause and interest of Lordly prelacy:</hi> witness the Spirit, which in some few from the beginning of the war, lifted up it self, in the strength of Christ, against the King with his party, as against a desperate enemy <hi>to the Lord Jesus his true seed and Kingdom,</hi> and a great friend to <hi>Antichrist and the carnal and persecuting Church,</hi> in all his Kingdoms.</p>
               <p>And, because we would now Demonstrate (for now it is time) that the <hi>Cause promoted in the Army</hi> was utterly <hi>another Cause,</hi> from <hi>that</hi> carried on by the <hi>Kirk of Scotland</hi> and its friends in <hi>England,</hi> we shall endeavour to state and plead it so, as that <hi>the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, the separated Congregations</hi> and their Friends, shall know where to finde it <hi>in the midst of all these shakings and turnings of things upside down,</hi> which have come to pass in these daies; provided, they seek for it, with their whole heart, and inquire after it, with their whole desire.</p>
               <p>First, The <hi>under-Officers and Souldiers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Sectaries Cause stated from the Armies Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</note> give us light towards the stating of <hi>this glorious Cause,</hi> in that their best Declaration at <hi>Muscleborough, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gust</hi> 1. 1650. when <hi>the light of the Lord seemed to shine upon their tabernacles,</hi> with greatest splendor: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring in one place,
<q>
                     <hi>They were abundantly satisfied in their Judgements and Consciences, that they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led forth by the Lord to be Instrumental to bring about that which was their continual prayer to God,</hi> viz. <hi>the Destruction of Antichrist, and the Deliverance of his Church and People;</hi> and they call this, <hi>the work of Jesus Christ.</hi> They go on to tell us, <hi>that they had singly in their eye the Destruction of Antichrist, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119051:21"/>the Advancement of the Kingdom of Jesus Christ,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>they are so far from resting satisfied in the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant, as any way useful to these ends, as that they intimate their fears, that the Interest of Jesus Christ, is only pretended to, and the Interests of this world, yea of Antichrist himself, was carried on, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Vizard.</hi> Nay, more then this, they declare, <hi>they were perswaded in their consciences, that he and his Monarchy was one of the ten Horns of the Beast spoken of</hi> Rev. 17.12, 13, 14, 15. <hi>and that he had shed much of the innocent bloud of the Saints in supporting the Beast; and therefore desired Justice, upon extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Impulses from the Lord,</hi> &amp;c.</q> So that it is plain, that the under-Officers were sensible <hi>(if they spake the truth from their hearts unto their Neighbours) of a Cause</hi> vastly differing from what Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> hath lately stated, and the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> in any of their Papers: stating it (in their Declaration before mentioned) so high and full, as if <hi>they were Fifth-Kingdom-men at the highest rate,</hi> with <hi>this super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>addition,</hi> in so many words, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <q>
                     <hi>We have not only proclaimed Jesus Christ, the King of Saints, to be our King by profession, but desire to submit to him upon his own terms, and admit him to the exercise of his Royal Authority in our hearts, sutable thereunto, and to follow him whithersoever he goeth,</hi> &amp;c.</q> Exceeding good words! we wait to see Actions proportioned to those words. If it be asked, whether the <hi>General and the great Commanders did own this excellent Declaration</hi> of his under-Officers;
<note place="margin">From Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s Letter.</note> our Answer is ready: For <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver Cromwell</hi> Esq; the Captain General, in a Letter of his, tels the <hi>Scots,</hi> that</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <q>the under-Officers &amp; Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in the English Army, <hi>had desired him to send to them this their Declaration: and to prove that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119051:21"/>he both read and approved</hi> this choice Paper, <hi>he tels the</hi> Scots, It is not a crafty politick one, but a plain, sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, spiritual one, such as it is, God knoweth, and God also will in due time make manifest. And do we mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply these words as mens? Or do we them for the Lord Christ and his peoples sake?</q> &amp;c. <hi>Concluding,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your humble Servant, <hi>O. Cromwell.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Thus far he: the History of whose Life and Death, since the Victory at <hi>Worcester, September</hi> 3. 1651. to the 3. of <hi>September,</hi> 1658. if described in lively colours, would exceedingly commend this <hi>glorious Cause,</hi> and justly condemn the <hi>Infamous A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postacy</hi> of this day: but however, he was one with this Paper, at that day, as is well known. And, as for the <hi>great Commanders,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">From a Paper sent by the gteat Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to their friends to pray for them.</note> there is a paper printed by them likewise, before their <hi>March to Scotland,</hi> (though almost forgotten) which will help to <hi>state the Cause,</hi> as the <hi>most noble Cause under Heaven;</hi> and that in such variety of good and full expressions, as may also answer the <hi>Fifth Kingdom-mens largest principles and Expectations.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">From the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals Speech to the little Assembly.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Beside <hi>these two Papers</hi> from the Army,
<note place="margin">From the prayers and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exercises of the Messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of several Churches meeting at <hi>Black-Fryers, London;</hi> and before them at <hi>Alhallows.</hi>
                  </note> there are several passages in the Speech made to the <hi>little As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly,</hi> by the late General: and there was a noble witness in the same Assembly, which will counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the Cause stated and asserted by the people aforesaid: not forgetting that testimony which was given to it from several separated Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and their Messengers in and about this City,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119051:22"/>for several years together, before the interruption (as it's now called) of the Long Parliament. From all which premised Considerations, and <hi>Survey of the Cause</hi> from the beginning of the War, we may safely conclude, that it is to be taken for granted, among the Inhabitants of these Nations,</p>
               <p>First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That <hi>Jesus Christ is the Lord, to the Glory of God the Father:</hi> that is, the person of the Lord Jesus Christ was exalted, to sit upon the throne of his Father <hi>David,</hi> at his Ascension into Heaven, and is now at Gods right hand, invested with all power in Heaven and Earth.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That in all Ages since his Ascension, he hath had a Cause of his own to Assert, Plead, and Defend against all opposition, on the behalf of himself and people, in distinction from all other Causes, concernments and interests in the world.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> His Cause is the most glorious under Heaven, being also of a very vast extent, and bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching forth its self into many distinct Heads, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to the particular truths of the Gospel (or the New Covenant) to be pleaded and promoted, in every Age, according to the Counsel of his own will.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> This Cause (or any part of it, so glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in it self, and in the eyes, both of the holy Angels, and of his true, illuminated Disciples) is not owned, entertained, or understood in the least, by the <hi>whole world that lieth in wickedness:</hi> the Jews, Turks, and Heathen, have no knowledge of it.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> the Papists, and their Church-officers, have been all along, enemies to that Cause or Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119051:22"/>of Christ and his people, which we have been promoting of late years, calling it Honourable, Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and Glorious. The Hereticks Cause is none of their Cause; and their Cause, is not our Cause.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, It is very improbable, if not impossible, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> that this <hi>glorious Cause</hi> should be <hi>rightly understood and esteemed by those Protestants,</hi> which are so far from <hi>walking worthy of the Gospel,</hi> the Cause and the Interest of our dear Lord, as that <hi>they are fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with all unrighteousness and ungodliness,</hi> and scoffers at the Cause, and the people that as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert it.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, So that this <hi>precious cause of Christ,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> with all its <hi>native Beauty,</hi> and <hi>superadded Ornaments,</hi> must be apprehended to be <hi>esteemed</hi> and <hi>received</hi> among <hi>THOSE ONLY</hi> who are one Spirit with the Lord Jesus Christ in this day, having the <hi>Spirit</hi> &amp; <hi>principle</hi> of it in the <hi>power of God, and not of man</hi> (&amp; his teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, or example): they alone, are able, &amp; have been enabled all along, not only to understand and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it, but to <hi>suffer for its sake.</hi> And all others who, in <hi>good Expressions, by tongue or pen,</hi> have been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to <hi>assert it</hi> when it was <hi>in Reputation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Feigned friends to the Best Cause, are its worst Enemies,</note> and yet have not <hi>written</hi> or <hi>spoken for it in true light and love,</hi> but with <hi>secret respects to worldly Advantages,</hi> are in danger, at one time or other, <hi>not only</hi> to <hi>decline</hi> and <hi>turn away; but also,</hi> to <hi>set up</hi> and <hi>Adore</hi> any other <hi>new Interest</hi> that will <hi>Accommodate the Flesh and the Lusts thereof.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>So that it is no marvel, that the <hi>former Language</hi> (at the <hi>Head-quarters,</hi> in the <hi>Gathered Churches,</hi> in several <hi>papers of the Army,</hi> in several <hi>printed Sermons</hi> and <hi>other Treatises</hi>) which sounded through the three Nations &amp; beyond the Seas, hath been <hi>almost
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119051:23"/>forgotten,</hi> and <hi>lost,</hi> for want of <hi>use,</hi> of <hi>exercise</hi> and <hi>improvement:</hi> the Reason is ready and at hand; Many were <hi>called</hi> (stirred up and gifted) to <hi>own</hi> the <hi>Cause of Christ,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Many called, but few cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen to plead the Cause of Christ in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous times.</note> to <hi>plead</hi> it, to <hi>contend</hi> for it, to <hi>exemplifie</hi> and <hi>adorn</hi> it; but few were <hi>chosen:</hi> for <hi>in time of temptation,</hi> many <hi>pretended friends</hi> were found to fall away, and embrace the next opportunity of <hi>worldly profit, honour,</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> to them and theirs.</p>
               <p>But,
<note place="margin">The Spirit of the true feed will not abate the Army one tittle of their Papers for the Cause.</note> know this for your <hi>better Information,</hi> Oh all you <hi>Leaders of the Army, both great and small,</hi> there is an <hi>ESCAPED REMNANT,</hi> that will not abate you so much as <hi>one sentence or phrase,</hi> no, not one <hi>Iota or tittle,</hi> of all those many excellent passages where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with those your Papers are richly <hi>bespangled,</hi> as with so many <hi>Rays of pure gold:</hi> concerning the <hi>ADVANCEMENT OF THE KINGDOM OF CHRIST,</hi> the <hi>DESTRUCTION OF THE KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOM OF THE BEAST,</hi> your <hi>FOLLOWING OF THE LAMB,</hi> your being <hi>THE ARMY OF THE LAMB:</hi> touching the <hi>WORK OF CHRIST, THE INTEREST OF OUR LORD;</hi> and whatsoever more there is of that nature: these are the <hi>SUBSTANCE</hi> and <hi>SPIRIT</hi> of the <hi>Good true Cause</hi> of God, of Christ, of his spiritual Church, of the oppressed groaning creation: there is neither <hi>sap</hi> nor <hi>savour,</hi> neither <hi>juyce</hi> nor <hi>spirit</hi> in all your papers, in comparison, if these and such like <hi>choice expressions</hi> of your love and good will to <hi>this Cause of Christ,</hi> were wanting in them.
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.7.</note>
                  <hi>Consider what is written, and the Lord give you understanding in all things.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119051:23"/>
               <head>SECT. VI. <hi>The Advance of the Cause after the Kings Death; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperous success in</hi> Ireland, <hi>putting a fresh lustre upon it. New Confederacies against it, betwixt the</hi> Scots <hi>and young</hi> Charles Stuart. <hi>The war in</hi> Scotland. <hi>Victory at Dunbar: that Day Twelve-moneth, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at</hi> Worcester. <hi>Mr.</hi> Love <hi>beheaded: other Presbyterian Ministers Imprisoned. Addresses to the General, after his return home, without effect. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresses to God, with good effect. The Sectaries begin to Differ among themselves, after these glorious salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The honest Sectary presseth forward. The selfish Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctary well satisfied with his present Attainments. The meeting at</hi> Alhallows, <hi>with its nature, and its conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences. The reviving of it (after its decay at</hi> Alhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows) <hi>at</hi> Blackfryers.</head>
               <p>NOt long before that <hi>notable Act of the Army in secluding</hi> those Members, which were <hi>basely Bargaining with the King</hi> at <hi>Newport,</hi> for all the <hi>Bloud, Sweat,</hi> and <hi>Treasure</hi> expended in the first and second War, The Good old Cause (as it is commonly called) was become (through ill-management, and the prevarication of some pretenders) a very <hi>Pitiful, Dull, Dry, Lean, Barren, Ill-favoured Thing;</hi> in a deep Consumption, without Life and Spirit, beauty or comliness, ready even to give up the Ghost. But upon the Recovery of it afterward, when the great Adversary was removed, by that <hi>fatal stroke,</hi> it became and appeared on a sudden in the eyes of thousands, the most <hi>lovely, lively, growing, sparkling, prosperous Cause</hi> in all the earth.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:119051:24"/>
               <p>For all its <hi>faithful friends and Advocates,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Relief of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </note> cannot, must not forget (though others do) how <hi>the Lord went forth with our Armies into</hi> Ireland: what a <hi>sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den turn of Affairs</hi> there was at <hi>Dublin,</hi> by a most wonderful Defeat immediately before their Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sportation, is most worthy of thankful remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance at this day: That City being one of the <hi>two last Morsels</hi> of all their prey and spoyl in that Nation; how was it taken <hi>from between their teeth,</hi> as they were ready to swallow it whole? What <hi>WRITTEN VENGEANCE was executed at</hi> Drohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,
<note place="margin">Justice at <hi>Drohedah,</hi> and <hi>Wexford.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>at</hi> Wexford, and at other places? The <hi>power</hi> and <hi>spirit</hi> of our <hi>Cause,</hi> was <hi>great</hi> and <hi>high</hi> after the <hi>Kings Death,</hi> more then at any time before. We looked upon the <hi>work of Justice</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spering under the <hi>Standard of the Interest of Christ,</hi> professedly displayed against the <hi>Interest of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ</hi> and his adherents in that whole Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>But whilst this <hi>Glorious Cause of Christ</hi> is thus pleaded with such wonderful success (now in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The War with the young <hi>Scotish</hi> King.</note> as formerly in <hi>England</hi>) the <hi>Solemn League<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> are <hi>combining</hi> against the <hi>Sectaries,</hi> once more. After many <hi>Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Treaties,</hi> and <hi>Proposals</hi> to and fro, betwixt <hi>young Charles</hi> and <hi>Them;</hi> the <hi>State of his Affairs</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strains him to <hi>entertain their Terms,</hi> and to joyn with the <hi>Scotish Kirk,</hi> and their friends in <hi>England.</hi> The <hi>Royal Diadem</hi> being full in his eye, and they inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to <hi>put it upon his head,</hi> it's the less to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at, that he should think meet to pretend a compliance with them. <hi>A STOOL OF REPEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TANCE is made ready for the poor young man,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to counterfeit a kinde of sorrow for <hi>his own sins
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119051:24"/>and the sins of his fathers house.</hi> Hereupon Arms are raised, another war is commenc'd, not now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>King and Bishops,</hi> on the one part, and <hi>the Parliament with the Puritans</hi> of all sorts, on the other part; nor betwixt the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Duke Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> as in the second War; but betwixt the <hi>most Orthodox Kirk of Scotland,</hi> with their new young King in the Head of them; and the <hi>Infamous Army of Sectaries</hi> sent thither, by the <hi>Parliament of England</hi> now ruling, without a <hi>King</hi> or <hi>House of Peers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>common people of Scotland</hi> were possessed by the <hi>Kirk-men,</hi> that these <hi>Hereticks and Sectaries,
<note place="margin">The <hi>English</hi> Forces call'd an Army of Sectaries.</note> were not like others of the children of men,</hi> but strange kinde of ugly Monsters, so deformed, that it was dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to look upon them, or come near them: That it was their duty to joyn as one Man, <hi>to cut them off from the face of the earth;</hi> with a <hi>thousand Instigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of like import. But the <hi>Issue at</hi> Dunbar <hi>was glorious on the Sectaries side.</hi> We carried the Cause,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dunbar</hi> Battel and Victory.</note> in the strength of Christ, whose it was, against the whole power of <hi>Scotland</hi> in Kirk and State; <hi>blessed for ever be his glorious Name.</hi> But within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass of one whole year, the <hi>Scots</hi> so bestir'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, that they marcht with <hi>another Army</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> and were <hi>high in their hopes,</hi> that the <hi>most Orthodox, reformed Church</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> should carry it at length against a <hi>People</hi> that were <hi>King-killers, Blasphemers of Christ, enemies to his Kirk,</hi> &amp;c. But the same Cause that prospered and prevailed <hi>Sept.</hi> 3. 1650. did likewise prevail <hi>Sept.</hi> 3. 1651.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Worcester</hi> fight and Victory.</note> It may easily be conceived, how the hearts and mouths of the <hi>Dissenting Brethren,</hi> and all their <hi>fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Sectaries</hi> were fil'd with joy: Daies of great solemnity in blessing and praising the Lord,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119051:25"/>with <hi>Psalms,</hi> and <hi>Hymns,</hi> and <hi>spiritual Songs,</hi> being observed by several <hi>separated Congregations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hitherto the Lord hath wonderfully helped the poor people, reproached under the name of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, Schismaticks,</hi> and <hi>Sectaries;</hi> not by the <hi>Prelats</hi> so much, as by the <hi>Presbyterian Brethren:</hi> but the Lord looked upon it, and required it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>General Cromwell</hi> (accounted the Head of these Sectaries) comes to <hi>Westminster in Triumph,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>O. Cromwell</hi> Returns home in Triumph.</note> met and attended on by many thousands of people; and among others, by the <hi>New-Church-Regiments,</hi> raised and armed by <hi>Authority of Parliament,</hi> as a <hi>Reserve to the Army,</hi> when it was in <hi>Scotland.</hi> Which Brigade of <hi>London-Sectaries,</hi> was a <hi>Grievous Eye-sore</hi> to the <hi>Classical Ministers</hi> and people of the same City.</p>
               <p>It is to be remembred, that <hi>many of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Ministers</hi> were, not long before the battel at <hi>Worcester,</hi> accused of <hi>High Treason,</hi> for holding cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondence with <hi>young Charles</hi> against the <hi>Infant-Commonwealth.</hi> Several <hi>eminent Ministers</hi> were <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Love</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> fight.</note> Mr. <hi>Love,</hi> after Tryal and Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was Beheaded. These passages were very strange, and <hi>Ominous</hi> to the <hi>declining Cause</hi> of the <hi>Scotish Covenant;</hi> but looked with a <hi>benign Aspect</hi> upon the <hi>Separate Congregations;</hi> where the <hi>Cause</hi> was kept alive in <hi>England</hi> at that day.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Captain General</hi> a foresaid, coming home, <hi>thus laden with Lawrel,</hi> upon the Account of all his victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious successes first in <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>O. Cromwell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> congratulated by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> then in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and last of all in <hi>Scotland;</hi> was entertained by the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as a most worthy and <hi>prosperous Captain.</hi> All their <hi>Forces</hi> having been committed to his <hi>Trust</hi> and <hi>Command,</hi> (with confidence of his faithfulness and Integrity) he having made, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119051:25"/>of the War, <hi>a great and high profession of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness.</hi> He was likewise <hi>entertained</hi> with <hi>congratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory speeches</hi> by the <hi>Messengers of several Churches,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">And by the Churches.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing their high esteem of him, as one of their <hi>Best Friends;</hi> and had accordingly, with great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, besought the Lord on his behalf, and of the whole Army, when venturing their <hi>lives in this glorious Cause.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not long after his return,
<note place="margin">Some honest Sectaries desire him to prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Cause of Christ.</note> (the <hi>solemn Day</hi> of publick praise and thanksgiving being over) it came to pass, that divers <hi>Officers and Members</hi> of several <hi>Congregations</hi> meeting privately together, who by the free Grace of God, had been preserved from the snares and temptations of this day (we mean, the great preferments to honour, power, profit, and other pleasing Delights of this wicked old world, wherein many of the <hi>Sectaries</hi> had lately been taken and entangled) did verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, upon prayer, conference, and consideration, that it was their <hi>present work and Duty,</hi> to be stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up the <hi>General</hi> and his <hi>great Commanders,</hi> to press forward in promoting that <hi>glorious Cause,</hi> (which they had declared for, before and after their march into <hi>Scotland</hi>) every where, and every way; and particularly, to quicken the <hi>Parliament</hi> to do some <hi>honest and honourable works,</hi> before they went off the <hi>publick stage:</hi> for now there was a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rumour of their putting a Period to their own power, in some convenient time.</p>
               <p>At the first, we found the <hi>General willing to hear us;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Their hopes frustrated.</note> desiring us to seek the <hi>Lord solemnly</hi> in a day of prayer; and he and his Officers would seek the Lord likewise by themselves: but not finding that acceptance afterward, which we hoped for, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119051:26"/>the <hi>many Promises, Ingagements, Letters, and other Papers</hi> which had come to our sight and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, concerning his and their readiness <hi>to serve the Lord and his People,</hi> if ever they should return in peace; we perceived, that <hi>Others about him,</hi> who had his ear, did instill and insinuate into his spirit, <hi>some principles</hi> and <hi>other matters</hi> of a tendency very different from our proposals.
<note place="margin">They cease their Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> Whereupon, after two meetings with him at <hi>Suffolk-house,</hi> we left him, and made no further Application to him; finding that divers <hi>self-seeking Officers and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Churches</hi> were willing to take up their rest, and <hi>pitch their Tents, where it was so good for them to be,</hi> in the midst of their new-gotten honour, power, and profitable places.</p>
               <p>Nevertheless,
<note place="margin">The meeting for Treating with the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, dissolved. New conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and counsels, how to plead the glorious cause of Jesus Christ.</note> after we had dissolved our first private Meeting, taken up as aforesaid, Two or three of us did, within a short space of time, consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what was meet for us and others, yet further to do, for the <hi>effectual prosecution of our blessed Cause,</hi> and the <hi>further service of our Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> in such a Day of mercy as this was. The Result was, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though our best friends, in whose hand there was power, did turn the deaf ear to our Proposals, yet there could be no ground to fear, that we should be so dismissed from the Throne of Grace, if we would make our prayers unto God, for the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of those <hi>blessed and excellent good things,</hi> which we had been lately labouring after, <hi>at the Head-quarters,</hi> and <hi>Suffolk-house,</hi> in vain, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out effect. It was accordingly agreed by those two or three, that, having no incouragement given from any Man or Men on earth (now that the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral had thus frustrated all our hopes, so soon
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119051:26"/>after <hi>Worcester</hi>-Fight) we would proceed in our intended course, and joyning with those of the same minde, would make <hi>earnest and uncessant Prayer unto our God and Father,</hi> for a <hi>gracious Answer</hi> in those particulars, which we had spread before the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and all to no purpose.</p>
               <p>Immediately hereupon,
<note place="margin">Another mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is set on foot publickly at <hi>Alhallows.</hi>
                  </note> there was <hi>another Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of divers <hi>Officers and Members of Churches,</hi> among whom some were Souldiers; &amp; in the close of a day of <hi>solemn seeking the face of God for Wisdome, Counsel, and Direction to our present Duty,</hi> (conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how hard it was like to go with the Cause of Christ) we did, in less then half an hours time, agree upon <hi>Six General Heads of Prayer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Cause is pleaded before the Lord in six Heads of Prayer.</note> of common concernment to the friends of that our present Cause; and to which Petitions, they could not but heartily say, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They are these which follow; we mean, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the spirit and substance of them.</p>
               <p>First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That the <hi>Kingdom of our Lord Jesus Christ</hi> may be exalted speedily in these Nations, and also in all the earth; and that whatsoever stood in the way of it, might be utterly pulled down, and brought to nothing.</p>
               <p>That all <hi>Corrupt, Wicked, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and ungodly Magistrates</hi> might be removed, and put out of place and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and that a Righteous generation of Rulers might be set up in their stead.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Idle, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Ignorant and scandalous Ministry</hi> might be laid aside, and put out of their respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Parishes; And that in their stead, the Lord
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119051:27"/>would anoint and send forth Pastors according to his own heart, such as might feed his people with knowledge and understanding.</p>
               <p>That that <hi>spirit of Division and Animosity</hi> which was found among his own People, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, that so we might all serve him with one consent.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Lord would effectually stir up the Parliament, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> the Army, and the Churches,</hi> to remember and perform all those <hi>just and good Promises, Ingagements,</hi> and <hi>Declarations,</hi> wherein they were openly and so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ingaged, in the dayes of their Distress.</p>
               <p>That, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> whereas there were <hi>Ambassadors coming from</hi> Holland, <hi>to Treat with the Parliament</hi> about some growing Differences and Discontents betwixt us and them; the Lord himself would so interpose by his special Providence, that no terms nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions might take place, which were in the least Derogatory or prejudicial to the Cause of Christ, and his Kingdom, now carrying on in these Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>We,
<note place="margin">A sweet Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony among Saints of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent forms and perswasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> who were present, must not bury in Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion, what <hi>onenesse of heart</hi> there was in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and what rejoycing, to observe of what conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence this might be in processe of time, if a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable measure of <hi>the Holy Unction</hi> should be given forth, for the promoting of this <hi>Gospel</hi>-DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIGN so dangerous to all the Kingdomes; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Rulers, and ungodly Ministers, in all the world.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:119051:27"/>
               <p>Accordingly, <hi>by the grace of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A lively Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit at the first coming toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> with some light and livelinesse of spirit, the first meeting was at <hi>All-hallows, Thamestreet</hi> London; The latter end of <hi>December</hi> 1651.</p>
               <p>This <hi>new thing in the Nation,</hi> gave an <hi>Alarm</hi> to <hi>Parliament, Army,</hi> and <hi>those Churches and Officers</hi> which had very far <hi>forsaken the Cause</hi> contended for, and had <hi>loved this present world.</hi> It was very offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive to all those <hi>selfish Sectaries,</hi> which had begun, and were going on, to inrich themselves, out of the <hi>publick Ruines.</hi> Those, who carried on this work, could not through grace be charged with those <hi>common Evils</hi> of <hi>covetousness, ambition,</hi> and <hi>screwing themselves</hi> into great places of profit, though it was endeavoured; and therefore, <hi>were the more bold to speak the word, without fear</hi> of such imputations. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many <hi>honest hearts,</hi> that frequented the meeting, did confess they found the <hi>presence,</hi> and <hi>spirit,</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of God more here then elsewhere, it being <hi>Generation-work,</hi> and the proper business of that Day.</p>
               <p>We gave <hi>an account</hi> of these things to divers at <hi>Somerset-house,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">We give an Account to Dissatisfied Brethren.</note> who were much offended at this sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and loud Alarm to the <hi>Selfish part of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed people:</hi> and in conclusion, having in <hi>a brotherly way, rehearsed the Matter unto them from the beginning,</hi> we told them, that by the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> we were resolved to <hi>follow the Lord in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this very day, many of us cannot tell where our <hi>blessed Cause</hi> was witnessed unto, so openly at that time, as it was in that Assembly.</p>
               <p>Yet afterward,
<note place="margin">A Death over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes this work also.</note> upon some particular emergent occasions, divers <hi>Leading men</hi> fell off, who at the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119051:28"/>first rejoyced and joyned in it: but the Truth is, it was plain afterward, that the <hi>spirit of the world</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried some of them away: others, by the <hi>scruples of their friends,</hi> did receive impressions of Discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, and so gave over. Insomuch that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the space of a year, or thereabout, there was a very sensible <hi>decay of Spirit</hi> in that meeting, to the grief of divers faithful friends.</p>
               <p>But it pleased the Lord to stir up two or three,
<note place="margin">Another-Essay by Messengers of Churches to plead the Cause.</note> to consider again what the <hi>true remnant of Jacob</hi> were capable to do for the <hi>Name and Cause of our Lord,</hi> so little spoken of and pleaded for at that time: for it is to be remembred, that the <hi>Great, and other Commanders</hi> of the Army, were for the most of them so imployed in setling and <hi>securing their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears,
<note place="margin">Great Officers otherwise im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed.</note> in parting and dividing their Parks, and their great Houses,</hi> that they had no leisure to appear in the <hi>work of Christ.</hi> And indeed, what could they do more, as Souldiers? considering there was no open potent Enemy to oppose them.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, it was a very difficult matter to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand where <hi>the Lord did delight to manifest his presence,
<note place="margin">War with the <hi>Dutch.</hi>
                     </note> at that time,</hi> until the <hi>war with Holland</hi> was brought upon us by an <hi>irresistible Dispensation:</hi> for by the Generality of the Parliament, it was avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by all means. But there were some who did verily beleeve, that the Lord would reckon with that people, <hi>for the Bloud of his Saints,</hi> which had been shed by those weapons that had been bought of them by the Queen of <hi>England:</hi> for if they had not furnished the King with weapons and Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Death, it had been very Difficult, if not impossible for him to have destroyed the lives of so many of his Best Subjects.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119051:28"/>
               <p>Those very few above mentioned, invited <hi>six se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Congregations,</hi> who were least <hi>leavened with the spirit of self-seeking,</hi> and most affected to the <hi>work of the day,</hi> to agree, and send each of them some of their number; who having most spirit and light, might appear <hi>as the Messengers of the Churches, and the Glory of Christ,</hi> in a publick way.</p>
               <p>Accordingly,
<note place="margin">The fast friends to the Cause come together with a fresh Spirit.</note> after once or twice meeting at <hi>London-house,</hi> and afterward at <hi>Blackfryers,</hi> We found some of the <hi>true Seed flocking together afresh,</hi> in a way of waiting upon the Lord, partly to hear those Scriptures opened, which concerned the <hi>blessed Interest of Jesus Christ;</hi> and partly to wrestle with the Lord again (after our former neglect) for the fulfilling of his Word, in <hi>the Destruction of</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, <hi>and advancement of the Kingdom of his dear Son.</hi> With other Petitions of <hi>General concernment</hi> to the <hi>Cause of God</hi> in these Nations, and beyond the Seas: for now, or about this time, the War with <hi>Holland</hi> was begun; whereupon, some of us, <hi>Girded up the loyns of our minds, and thanked God, and took Courage,</hi> (as <hi>Paul</hi> did when <hi>the Brethren met him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act: 28.15.</note> before he came at <hi>Rome</hi>).</p>
               <p>The proper work of these <hi>Messengers of the Churches</hi> aforesaid,
<note place="margin">The Work of the Meeting at <hi>Blackfryers.</hi>
                  </note> was publickly to own, and plead <hi>that glorious Cause of Christs Kingdom and Interest</hi> in the Nations, which had been declared for by the whole Army in the day of their straits, with great power and spirit; but now was very little considered and prosecuted, in comparison of their former forwardness and affection.</p>
               <p>Accordingly, There was a <hi>loud Testimony</hi> given, by the Assistance of the Spirit, unto <hi>the Work of the day;</hi> although withall, we must confess, that <hi>the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119051:29"/>Gospel of the Kingdom</hi> was published with a great mixture of <hi>humane frailty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 4.13.</note> (or <hi>the infirmity of the stesh,</hi> as the Apostle speaks). It may be the Lord so ordered it, that it might be for judgement to those poor wretches whose hearts began to wax dull and hard, and were become weary of the <hi>spiritual worth of that Truth and work,</hi> which God was then, and is still, lifting up, and bringing forth in the sight of all the Nations.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spirit</hi> which prevail'd at the <hi>Head-quarters,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The General vexed at the Testimony managed at <hi>Blackfryers.</hi>
                  </note> and elsewhere, was wonderfully displeased with us, for so <hi>publickly witnessing</hi> against those palpable self-seeking practises which were pursued with great eagerness <hi>in the Army, the Parliament, and the Churches,</hi> to the great dishonour of that blessed Cause, which yet they pretended to love with all their Hearts. Oh the Lukewarmness of that time, compared with former life and warmth! Oh the covetous practises in all <hi>Committees, Courts, Offices!</hi> how did the Speaker upbraid and reproach the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered Churches, when he told some of us to our faces, that the Parliament had bestowed upon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the Members of the Churches aforesaid (and the Best of them too, that they could hear of) several places of Trust, of great trust in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and yet within a little time they were found as Arbitrary, and oppressive, and self-seeking, as any other! and we knowing it to be too true, that divers made more haste to be rich, then to do Justice, were ashamed, and could not plead their Cause; but were constrained to bear our <hi>publick Testimony</hi> against such publick unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Miscarriages of our Brethren, so very like those unworthy <hi>Jewes,</hi> who began to oppresse the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119051:29"/>people assoon as they were come out of the House of Bondage: see <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5. But observe the Issue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII. <hi>The Long Parliament Dissolved. The little Assembly set up in their stead. The Generals Speech to them. The Cause prospers all the time of their sitting, in the War with</hi> Holland: <hi>they are dismissed the</hi> 12. Decemb. 1653. <hi>The glorious Cause of Christ betrayed by its pretended friends. The sum of all the Causes which have been pleaded upon the stage of Great</hi> Britain, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>this last twenty years.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT pleased the Lord,
<note place="margin">The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</note> in the deep Counsel of his wisdom and will, to <hi>necessitate the Parliament and Army into mutual unkindnesses and Jealousies:</hi> that seeing they would not agree together to lift up his Son, and exalt his Interest, they should so far disagree amongst themselves, as that a dangerous Rupture should follow unavoidably: which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly came to pass, <hi>April</hi> 20. 1653.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Contempt,
<note place="margin">Under great Contempt.</note> under which the Parliament-men did then fall,</hi> was very exceeding great and strange; the hand of the Lord is to be acknowledged by them and us, with Reverence and godly Fear. Was it not wonderful, that such a <hi>renowned Senate, so prosperous and victorious over all their Adversaries,</hi> should be pull'd out of their places, and put out of doors by their own Servants, whom they had so carefully paid and provided for? What ever secret Design was underneath, yet certainly there was some <hi>accursed thing</hi> in the midst of them, which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119051:30"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:119051:30"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:119051:31"/>provoked the eyes of his glory, who is a Jealous God, and will not be mock'd by those who were so often saved by him. Oh that they might not be found stumbling at the same stumbling stone, the second time!</p>
               <p>In the next place,
<note place="margin">The little As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly.</note> a <hi>new Face of affairs appears upon the stage,</hi> such as had not been seen or read of in any former Generation.</p>
               <p>The Kings Prerogative is utterly perished. The priviledges of Parliament are broken with a great breach, which will never be throughly healed. And now the Liberty of the people (upon the old Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of choosing their Representatives) is also made void, and of none effect: <hi>for the Army pretend to roll the Government of this Nation upon the Saints, as Saints.</hi> And to that end, call together a company of them from all parts of the Nation, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, and to exercise power and Authority over the Nation, <hi>in the Name of the Lord Jesus,</hi> as if they would <hi>introduce the Kingdom of Christ,</hi> or the fifth Kingdom.</p>
               <p>These things are declared by <hi>General Cromwell,</hi> unto those persons met together by vertue of the Call given to them, in that Speech of his in the Councel-Chamber, upon the 4. of <hi>July</hi> 1653. some of the words and passages are worthy to be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>And give me leave to begin thus.
<note place="margin">Part of the Speech to the little Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly by Gen. <hi>Cromwell.</hi>
                     </note> I confess I never looked to see such a Day as this, (it may be, nor you) when <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> shall be owned, as he is <hi>this day,</hi> and in this world: <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> is owned <hi>this day</hi> by you all, and you own him by your wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingness in appearing here. And you manifest <hi>this,</hi> (as far as poor Creatures can) to be <hi>a Day of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119051:31"/>the Power of Christ,</hi> by your willingness. I know you remember that Scripture, Psal. 110.3. <hi>Thy people shall be willing in the DAY Of THY POWER;</hi> God doth manifest it to be <hi>a Day of the power of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ.</hi> He goeth on. Having, through so much Bloud, and so many trials as have been upon these Nations, made this to be one of the great Issues thereof, to have a People called to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority, upon <hi>THIS AVOWED AC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COUNT. God hath owned his Son by this;</hi> and <hi>you by your willingness do own Jesus Christ:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for my part, I confess, I did never look to see such a fight, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And a little further, He tels them upon that place of <hi>Isa.</hi> 43.21. You are as like the forming of God, as ever people were, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I say, you are called with an high Call: and why should we be afraid to say or think, that this way may be the door to usher in things which God had promised, and prophesied of; and to set the hearts of his people to wait for? We know who they are that shall war with the Lamb against his enemies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He brings in that of <hi>Daniel, And the Kingdom shall not be delivered to another people.</hi> Truly God hath brought it into your hands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Then he proceeds, after two or three Scriptures quoted, in his own Name, and in the Name of his fellow-Officers, to <hi>Commend them to the Grace of God,</hi> and to the guidance of his Spirit; having thus far served you, or <hi>rather our Lord Jesus Christ in it,</hi> we are (as we hope) and shall be, ready in our stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, according as the providence of God shall lead us, to be subservient <hi>to the work of God,</hi> and the <hi>AUTHORITY WHICH WE RECKON, GOD
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119051:32"/>HATH SET OVER US.</hi> And so the Instrument, by which he delivered up the Supreme Power and Government of these Nations (out of the hands of the King, the Parliament and Army) into the Hands of This Number of godly men, as such, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing received and read (or Read and received) they were left to the guidance of God.</p>
               <p>Undoubtedly, Here was more of the <hi>Counsel and Providence of God in this solemn Speech and Action,</hi> then he himself, or any other then present, did well understand, or, then is understood unto this very day.</p>
               <p>What <hi>Underhand dealing there was in all this,</hi> is best known to the Lord; but the Lord hath regard to the Thing it self. And we are perswaded he will make it signifie something yet more, before he hath done <hi>Changing the Nation from vessel to vessel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This People,
<note place="margin">The Cause prospereth in the time of the little As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly.</note> though they were so yoked and mingled as they were, did set their hearts, (I mean, the faithful among them) <hi>to follow the Lord, and to serve him in the Kingdom of his Son:</hi> and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all the <hi>crafty contrivances of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents seed,</hi> yet the <hi>work and Cause</hi> prospered in their hands: the War with <hi>Holland</hi> was signally owned and carried on, even to the amazement of all. We know what kinde of people they were, that appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended all was lost. We remember the occasion of their pulling down, <hi>after the Army had so solemnly given up all into their hands.</hi> We have not forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten who made Bonfires for joy at this Change: nor can we choose, but observe and consider (with some awe upon our hearts) what is become of those,
<note place="margin">Whalley, Goff, White.</note> who were instruments to scatter those Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of our Lord which were so cordial to that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119051:32"/>blessed interest of Christ, pretended to, a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by the General and his Officers. The Lord well knows, who prevaricated with that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cause, after so many pretences of friendship to it. And the inhabitants of <hi>England</hi> shall know it, in due time, if they do not yet understand where the miscarriage was, at that day.</p>
               <p>But now,
<note place="margin">The Apostacy of the Army.</note> we want words whereby to Represent that Abomination that made Desolate, and laid in the dust the most honourable Interest under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. The same persons that had cried, <hi>Hosanna to the son of David,</hi> did afterward, cry, <hi>Crucifie him, Crucifie him.</hi> That <hi>General,</hi> Those <hi>great Commanders,</hi> Those <hi>under-Officers</hi> and <hi>Souldiers,</hi> which had pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly owned and submitted unto the <hi>Lord Jesus,</hi> by word and writing, in as choyce and full expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as any in the <hi>New Testament,</hi> do now, all on a sudden (without consulting the light, the prayers, the spirit, the faith, the wisdom of the <hi>true Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant)</hi> lift up an Idol into the Throne of Supream Authority in these Nations, which were to be Governed by none other then the <hi>Lord Jesus Christ himself.</hi> And being absolved from their former <hi>solemn Ingagements</hi> against Kingship (by a new kinde of Papal Dispensation) they do not onely relinquish and renounce the <hi>Cause,</hi> the <hi>Interest,</hi> the <hi>service</hi> and <hi>work</hi> of Him that was their <hi>Saviour</hi> and <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> in all their late Dangers and Distresses, and to whom, they had, as it were, sworn fealty and allegiance; but also, do set up, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their <hi>Own Inventions,</hi> that new, upstart Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Interest, which (like other works of Darknesse) was conceived, formed, and brought forth by the power of that Spirit which <hi>worketh ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119051:33"/>in the Children of this world,</hi> in opposition to <hi>the Children of light, and the Spirit which is of God.</hi> And having so done,
<note place="margin">An engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment contrary to the former.</note>
                  <hi>A new Engagement</hi> is formed, for the binding of the Army fast and firm for the Defence of that <hi>Treasonable usurpation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>private, proud, self-Interest</hi> and <hi>Cause,</hi> get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon the Stage, <hi>Oh how did it vaunt it self? how uncomely did it behave it self? how did it Brow-beat the friends of the former noble Cause with all manner of supercilious Disdaines? what Oratory and Tears, what Threatnings and flatteries were made use of, for the magnifying of this PITIFUL CHANGELING, as if it had been the Goddesse Diana,
<note place="margin">Acts 19.35.</note> and the Image which fell down from Jupiter?</hi> What reproachful language against all Valiant Assertors of former principles of Justice and true freedom, in opposition to this <hi>Monstrous Government?</hi> They are <hi>Traytors,</hi> and shall be dealt with as <hi>Traytors.</hi> How many Pursevants and Men-catchers, Spies and Emissaries are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to lay Snares and Traps for those, who will not fall down and <hi>Worship this ugly Image?</hi> And which is the most <hi>confounding consideration</hi> of all, how, Oh how was the <hi>Name of God blasphemed</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Cavaliers, and the Neighbour-Nations, because of that <hi>Hypocrisie</hi> and <hi>deceit,</hi> that <hi>falshood</hi> and <hi>Treachery</hi> which appeared in the <hi>forehead of the Army,</hi> after they had with one accord declared for the <hi>Interest and Kingdom of Jesus Christ?</hi> And now to set up the most <hi>Monstrous Monarchy,</hi> the most <hi>Arbitrary power</hi> that could be invented by a <hi>perfidious Generation of Professors,</hi> how did this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their faces with shame, who were upright of heart, and desired in good earnest to <hi>follow the Lambe whithersoever he should go?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119051:33"/>
               <p>But, <hi>This abomination</hi> is thrust headlong off the Stage, by the wonderfull power of our God. There are and were an hidden people that would give the Lord no rest, till vengeance was executed upon that spirit of Hypocrisie and Apostacie, which was carrying us back to the Garlick and Onions of Egypt. <hi>Salvation, and Glory, and Honour, and Power be unto the Lord our God, and to the Lamb, for ever and ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Here followeth a Table of the several and Joynt Interests which have been upon the publick stage, since <hi>1640.</hi> Computed and cast up in a Readiness, principally for the use of the Fifth-Kingdom-men, or the subjects of <hi>Messiah</hi> the Prince.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Interest of English Monarchy and Prelacy, <hi>1640.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe <hi>distinct Interest</hi> of the <hi>King of Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> was (1) to fortifie and defend to the utmost extremity, his <hi>own unbounded Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> against the long threatned, and now near ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching <hi>Inundation</hi> of a very highly <hi>discontented and oppressed populacy.</hi> And in order thereunto, (2.) to subdue and keep down the <hi>Puritans</hi> and other publick-spirited men, <hi>Lovers of true liberty and righteousness:</hi> which the better to effect, it was necessary for him to maintain the <hi>Star-Chamber</hi> and <hi>High Commission Courts,</hi> as having a <hi>Notorious Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy</hi> to that noble and <hi>Masculine Spirit,</hi> which now began to struggle and to stir strongly, in several corners of the Nation, Night and Day.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:119051:34"/>
                  <p>The <hi>Distinct Interest</hi> of the <hi>Lord Bishops,</hi> was, with all their might, to maintain the <hi>Ancient Dignity, and power of the Spiritualty,</hi> against the Invectives and oppositions of the <hi>Puritans</hi> and <hi>their partakers;</hi> and in order to that design, they in endeavoured all they could, to put manacles worse then those of <hi>Iron,</hi> upon those hands, which they suspected would take the first opportunity to pluck their <hi>Miters off their Heads.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Joynt Interest of King and Bishops,</hi> was to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their All of power and policy, for the <hi>mutual succour, support,</hi> and <hi>advancement</hi> of each other, above and against all opposers: And that upon this foundation; <hi>No Bishop, no King:</hi> and <hi>è converso; No King, no Bishop.</hi> And so it came to passe: for the <hi>Crown</hi> and the <hi>Miter,</hi> the <hi>Scepter</hi> and the <hi>Crosier,</hi> did flourish and fade together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Interest of the Long Parliament, <hi>1640.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The <hi>Interest of the Parliament,</hi> at the beginning, was to recover and secure their own and the free-peoples <hi>priviledges, liberties, properties,</hi> out of the reach of <hi>Monarchical and Prelatical Incroachments and Innovations;</hi> and to that end, the <hi>Puritans</hi> (both Conformists and Non-conformists) which were an illightned, stirring spirited people, and other honest and generous persons, affecting the <hi>noble Principles</hi> of Freedom, Justice, and good Laws, and withall, mortal enemies to the <hi>Interest of Court-Tyanny,</hi> Lust and Luxury, were called upon and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to joyn with them in the prosecution of those publick and common concernments for the Free-people.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119051:34"/>
                  <head>The Interest of the Puritans and their Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, <hi>1640.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>It was to obtain <hi>Liberty of Conscience</hi> out of the hands of the <hi>Romish-English-Hierarchy,</hi> which had continually vexed and persecuted them for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness sake; and to reduce the Kings preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to a narrower compass, within the Bounds of Law and Reason: and for more then these things they did not hope, at that day; but joyned with the Parliament upon that account, as appears by the Protestation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Interest of the Covenanters both <hi>Scotish</hi> and <hi>English</hi> after the war begun.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Interest</hi> of that party, was to overturn the Ancient, superstitious imperious form of <hi>Church-State</hi> in <hi>Doctrine, Worship,</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> by <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, Service-Book,</hi> and <hi>Canons,</hi> compelling to a <hi>CONFORMITY</hi> in all thing; and in stead thereof, to erect and introduce a <hi>New Carnal Church-state</hi> in <hi>Doctrine, Worship,</hi> and <hi>Discipline,</hi> by a <hi>Confession, Directory,</hi> and <hi>Synodical Assemblies,</hi> with a Proviso for <hi>UNIFORMITY</hi> in those things, the better to order their Brethren, who were not free to walk with them in those untrodden paths.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Interest of the Non-conformists and Sectaries at the same times.</head>
                  <p>Their <hi>Interest</hi> was to <hi>take hold of the present Oportunity</hi> to stand upon their Guard, in Defence
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119051:35"/>of their <hi>Just Liberties</hi> (purchased by Christ, and permitted by the Parliament) against both <hi>Prelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> and <hi>Synodical, pretended Jurisdiction</hi> over them: And beyond this, they did not seem to desire to attain, in that Day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Interest of the Remaining part of the Long Parliament, which cut off the late King, <hi>1648.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Their <hi>Interest</hi> was to abolish <hi>King-ship</hi> with its chargeable <hi>Appurtenances,</hi> and to introduce the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of a Free-state</hi> in stead thereof; which made a <hi>substantial Alteration</hi> in the Cause carried on till that Day. And the better to effect this Alteration, as also to secure themselves and their friends; It concerned them to ingage their Army and the Nations, in this <hi>new Establishment, without a King or House of Peers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Interest of <hi>O. P.</hi> commonly called in the three Nations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Their Lord Protector.</head>
                  <p>His <hi>proper Interest</hi> was, so soon as he had <hi>usur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the supreme civil Power,</hi> to secure and to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish it to <hi>Himself,</hi> and to <hi>his Family,</hi> against the <hi>Interest of the Stuarts</hi> and all their friends; as also against those <hi>Dissatisfied and Discontented Spirits,</hi> which hated Tyranny of a <hi>New Edition,</hi> with a more deadly hatred then that of the <hi>Old Form.</hi> In order unto which <hi>Security</hi> and <hi>Establishment,</hi> It con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned him to ingage the <hi>Corporations,</hi> the <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Great Lawyers,</hi> the <hi>Time-serving, Self-seeking Divines</hi> of all sorts and forms, the <hi>Souldiers</hi> and all, to stand by him, till he could procure or make
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119051:35"/>
                     <hi>(viis &amp; modis)</hi> such a <hi>Parliament,</hi> as would <hi>confirm him in the Throne,</hi> according to his own minde and will: and in the interim, it was his business, by Law (calculated for the Meridian of his own exaltation) to <hi>apprehend, imprison,</hi> and <hi>put to death,</hi> all his opposers, whether friends or enemies to the Commonwealth. The Instruments used by him, for the inforcing of which Law or Laws against pretended Treason and Traitors, were multitudes of <hi>Pursevants, Catchpoles, Spies, Spirits, Trapanners,</hi> and suck like <hi>Base Vermin,</hi> that use to creep and sneak in every corner, for the service of <hi>usurping upstarts</hi> in all Generations.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Interest of the True Commonwealths<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, at this Day.</head>
                  <p>His <hi>Proper Interest,</hi> is to <hi>preserve, defend,</hi> and <hi>promote</hi> the <hi>PUBLICK,</hi> and, in that, his own Good, by all honest and honourable means, against the <hi>private Interest,</hi> of those <hi>two Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> which would have put and kept an into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable <hi>yoke of Bondage,</hi> upon the necks of the well-affected people of these Nations, so wonderfully saved by the Lord.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Interest of the Real Fifth-Kingdom-men, in this day.</head>
                  <p>Their <hi>proper Interest</hi> is, in the Noblenesse of a True Gospel-spirit, and in proportion to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of Grace and gifts bestowed upon them for the service of their Lord, to indeavour the supplanting and <hi>destroying of Antichrist and his Interest,</hi> both at
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119051:36"/>home and abroad, &amp; to improve with all diligence their Time and Talents for the <hi>Advancement of the Kingdom of the Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> throughout all the earth. In order whereunto, They are to <hi>save them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves from that untoward Generation which will not have Christ to reign over them:</hi> And uniting together in one Spirit, to become a <hi>peculiar people</hi> (or, as it were, a <hi>Nation in the midst of the Nation)</hi> waiting for the word of Command from their Leader, <hi>to execute the vengeance written against Babylon,</hi> for being <hi>drunk with the bloud of the Saints, and with the bloud of the Martyrs of Jesus.</hi> Amen, Halleluiah.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Conclusion.</head>
               <p>THis <hi>Cause and Interest</hi> of our <hi>dearest Redeemer</hi> and his faithfull servants will appear again, even in its <hi>RESURRECTION-GLORY,</hi> ere it be long. He must increase, His proud Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titors must still decrease. Prepare, (Oh all ye hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Ones!) for those <hi>shoutings,</hi> and those <hi>Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations</hi> to the <hi>King of Saints,</hi> which will make the earth to shake, which will shake the very founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the <hi>Kingdom of the Beast.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Cause and Interest</hi> last stated, will be <hi>Amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> in the eyes of all the Nations in due time. It will swallow up into victory all <hi>contrary Causes</hi> and <hi>Interests</hi> whatsoever, as <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod devoured the Rods of the Magicians of <hi>Egypt,</hi> in that day.</p>
               <p>It is built upon a Rock, the Rock of ages; the Windes and Waves cannot undermine it, or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it. The <hi>Immutability of Gods Counsel</hi> bears it up.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:119051:36"/>
               <p>The <hi>wisdom of God,</hi> the <hi>power of God,</hi> the <hi>faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of God</hi> is ingaged to promote <hi>this Interest.</hi> How many have spoyled themselves and their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick Designs, by falling upon <hi>this stone!</hi> It will at length, in the appointed Season, fall upon all its enemies, and <hi>grind them all to powder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whosoever pleads <hi>This Cause,</hi> and is called of God to be an Advocate for <hi>This Interest,</hi> in the light and power of the <hi>eternal Spirit,</hi> will finde such <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Incouragements,</hi> that he shall not fear the <hi>face,</hi> the <hi>power,</hi> the <hi>Designs,</hi> the <hi>Enmity</hi> of any Person or People whatsoever.</p>
               <p>Courage, Courage, dear Hearts! The <hi>Great Whore which hath corrupted the earth with her fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and hath shed the bloud of the Saints of the most High, for so</hi> many hundred years, <hi>is to be stript naked, is to be made Desolate; Her flesh is to be eaten; she is to be burnt with fire, and the Lord God Omnipotent is to reign immediately hereupon:</hi> see <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.6.</p>
               <p>You are invited to be in a readinesse, and at an hours warning, to <hi>plead</hi> and to <hi>promote</hi> this <hi>blessed businesse:</hi> you shall have the Assistance of the <hi>Elect Angels,</hi> who have long since voted it before the Throne, that the <hi>Lamb that was slain is worthy to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive power, and riches, and wisdom, and strength, and honour, and glory, and blessing.</hi> Let us Eccho Back to them the same language, and say with them, and <hi>all the Saints, in faith, and hope, and love;</hi> Amen, <hi>and</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>